1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind
throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening everybody. Your listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
We are back. It is our first live show since the great flood
In the chestertun-
studio that happened right before Great Lent. My co-hosts father Stephen D'Young is with
me from Lafayette Louisiana and I'm father-interest Stephen Damick in Emmaus, the Commonwealth of
Pennsylvania. And if you're listening to this live and I hope you are, you can call it live.
That's right. It's happening. Thank you for reminding me that this is live radio.
Yes. You can call it. You can call it. It erupt each other.
Yeah, you should off. Don't do that.
Yeah, it's fine. It's okay. You can call us though at 855 AF radio
which is 855-237-2346 and
Machen's Kateru will be taking your calls and we're going to get to those in the second part of our show.
So one of our perennial topics on this show is how one reads the Bible. This is a critical question
for all Christians. Related to this is how one understands history both as part of our biblical
reading methodology.
and also as people looking at the historical narratives that are within the Bible.
Now, while we've made many comments over our few dozen episodes about this topic,
we've never done an episode focusing on it specifically.
So what you're going to hear in this episode is a methodology for reading the Bible
that we believe not only actually works, but also is what one sees revealed
in how the Orthodox Church fathers read the Bible,
and even more importantly, how we see the Orthodox Church reading the Bible
with in his
divine services. And we're also going to let you know why we so often start our episodes
with Genesis way back at the dawn of history. So let's start with this question of history.
So Father Stephen, what exactly is history? Well, before we go there, I feel like we need
to address an elephant to the room. Okay. Not the flood, right? People know about the flood.
Yeah, it's true. It was not the flood that we usually talk about though. It was another
flood. Right. It's it's it's it's other. Did you get this message from
Bobby Maddox? No. I get this message for it. He's apparently hiding out in Honduras. Did you
know about this? Oh, oh, I think he needs financial assistance. Is that right? He wants us to
send him lawyers, guns, and money in that order. Wow. So I don't know what's going on.
But if you see Bobby Maddox, help the man. You know, it's weird how many friends I have that have
this problem.
I get emails from them all the time.
Oh, okay, but I haven't gotten this one. Yeah, it's true. Maybe they could all pitch in together and help each other
Also also for listeners
Pay close attention because at one point during this episode
We are going to say something nice
About George William Frederick Hagle. I feel like we should have had theme music for when you said that
George William Friedrich Engel
I mean, I'm saying, you know, when we're gonna, you know, it was just such a dramatic moment, right? I feel there's been music to go along with. I mean, you know, I'm just throwing that out there. Play some Beethoven or something. Yeah.
I mean, he is he is one of our 19th century German friends. So I guess he does appear within that August assemblage, but not normally independently as he will this evening.
assemblage, but not normally independently as he will this evening.
So, yeah.
since we're going to be talking about history here that might clue you in as to why he might come up.
So yeah, part of where we have to start in terms of how to read the Bible,
not because it's necessary germane to the Bible, but because of the modern history,
especially the last couple of centuries of biblical interpretation and biblical studies.
right and the way
the understanding of history has gotten all wrapped up with that and sort of poisoned the well
in terms of how the scriptures are read by just about everybody. And so as you asked the question,
what is history, the answer that you would commonly get to that question changed
at the end of the 18th and beginning of the 19th century.
There was a transition that happened in terms of what people's understanding was of what history is.
So before that, if we go back before that, we go back into any pre-modern period.
And this is true from ancient times, really up through the Middle Ages, the medieval period.
The idea of history was very different than the modern one.
You had...
Basically in Europe and in other Christian cultures, up to that point, you had three main sources
for history. And when you studied history, it would sort of be these three things woven together.
All right, so one of those was the Bible, the Scriptures, particularly in the Old Testament,
in so far as they described.
Sir.
ancient ancient events. Then added into that would be various extrabiblical literature. So,
for example, the book of Enic that we've talked about before on the show many, many times,
in various contexts. Long after it was settled that for everybody but the Ethiopians that that's not
part of the biblical canon, long after that it was still being used in historical chronicles.
in the Stan the West.
Right, I recall you mentioning a Byzantine chronicler,
you know, George and Carlos.
Yeah, when was he?
He was in the end of the eighth century,
beginning of the ninth century.
Yeah, and so he's treating Inoc is basically
one of those historical sources
that everybody needs to read if you can understand history.
Right, filling in a bunch of things in and around,
you know, especially the book of Genesis.
Right.
Obviously with first genocence.
There were other sort of these both second-tepal Jewish literature that had been saved and preserved
mostly in Christian monastic settlements, and then also some of the Christian extrobiblical
literature stuff like the Gospel of Nicodemus and those kind of things, and martyrologies,
and those kind of things that would get incorporated. And then sort of on the other end from the Bible,
you would study, if you studied history at that time, you would study classics.
the Greek and Roman classics.
That was the sort of civilizational level, as opposed to the spiritual levels,
the way we would divide it, but they did not so divide it. They sort of blended it all together.
It's sometimes very interesting ways, but we won't digress on that too much.
But even into the 9th, 10th, 11th, 12th centuries in the Byzantine Empire,
Empire, they were writing commentaries on the Iliad and the Odyssey for X.
example, right? Right? And those were still being used for education. And so from these
sort, these narrative sources, there would be sort of a master narrative woven together.
That would be the history, the story of a particular people, right? Whether it's bead helping
do this kind of thing for the English people, whether it's UCBS Obsessoria.
wanting to do this for sort of the Christians of the Byzantine Empire, of the Roman Empire,
dozens of other examples, right? But you're weaving this together and you come to a story that begins with
somewhere around the creation of the world and ends with the present day of that people in the place where they dwell.
exactly. And that story then...
tells the story of where that people came from, how they got where they are now, how they
became a people, what sort of values or virtues characterize that people, and then who they're
going to be going forward.
Right. And the attention is not to sort of claim always. I mean, I think in some cases,
there was this claim that the particular people who are writing this story are, you know,
pinnacle of history or the center of the world right
or something like that, but rather it's just like, well, this history is written for these people
by these people. And so it makes sense that, you know, all the world's history up to this point
for us leads to here and now where we are, right? It's a kind of, it's a kind of, it's like if you're
studying genealogy, you know, everyone's really ultimately interested in genealogy as it leads down
to one point at the very bottom. And that's you, you know, everything in front of that is really interesting,
but you're not gonna...
follow all the branches out to everybody else. You might be interested in ones that are
closely related to you, but you know, the fact that, for instance, that pretty much every
single person within a European descent is probably descendants from Charlemagne. Doesn't
mean you're going to be following all of those stories. You're mostly just kind of interested
in you and your second and third and maybe like fourth cousins potentially.
Yeah, unless you're a Mormon and then it fans out in all. Oh, yeah, there's no, there's no limit there.
Yeah, yeah.
And so that's it's the story of those people who are standing there and it's being told and
re-told to those people who are standing there, right? So yes, the English people did not particularly
care about the history of the dramatic tribes except as it related to the English people.
Right. So but also that means that there's no idea
Like...
what we take for granted now, this division between subjectivity and objectivity.
Right. Right. They were not trying to give an objective look.
The history of their people and describe all of the events, works and all. Right.
Now the story was being told with a particular purpose. Right. And the people who were mentioned
in the story were mentioned for particular reasons because they were good examples or bad examples
or something they did became important or could be important.
the future or was to be emulated or was not to be emulated.
Right.
You can see this, for instance, even just the way that we tell American history.
We've had what 46 presidents now, I think.
And yet even people who are moderately familiar with American history, or even very familiar,
could not tell you much about most of them.
There's just certain key ones along the way.
And that's just even within our country's history.
Right. I mean, you don't have a bust of James K. Polk, the Napoleon of the West.
It's so weird, right? Or Millard Fillmore, you know?
It's true. It's true. I mean, I know the ones generally that were, you know, shot.
Those are the ones I remember the most. I don't know why. But, um,
but it's true that that, um, like the way that people feel good or bad about Abraham Lincoln
is just going to be simply different than the way that they feel about William Howard Taft.
and end-
Lincoln is considered to be much more significant for American story than Taft ever will probably
be probably be.
Actually, historically, if you had a time machine and you went back to just the right time
and assassinated William Howard Taft, you could prevent the Russian Revolution and at least
one of the world wars.
Wow.
But that's a subject for another time.
That's right.
That's a different podcast.
That's for a late night podcast we do it two in the morning everybody.
There, uh...
So but taft aside.
Yes, right?
And I mean, just taking a biblical example, that's what St. John says at the end of his
gospel, right?
Right.
There's not enough books in the whole world for me to write down everything that Christ
said and did, right?
But these things are written down so that you may believe and believing you may have
life in his name.
Yeah.
The gospels are not biography in the way that we do it now.
Right.
So you're saying, this is, I'm not being objective.
I'm very much not being objective.
Right? This is with a particular purpose.
And that's how all history was done.
Right? That's why all history was done.
And that's why even if you're living, if you're going to the
university of Paris in the 13th century, and you study history,
you're going to be studying the Roman Empire.
Right. Even though they're not Romans, which is a long way in the past.
Right?
But it was because
there were key elements that were seen there. It's selective. And so these stories
were crafted deliberately. One of the best examples of that is when Octavian
became Caesar Augustus, he commissioned his Virgil to write the Aneid.
To write a new, this is the history of Rome culminating in Augustus. And he
connected it.
to the Greek founding myths, right?
Because it connects it to the Iliad.
And so you see something that happens here
with empires, right?
Empires when they write their history,
they incorporate the histories of the people
who they conquered.
Yeah, and what's interesting is like,
that same act gets done.
Like if you read, if you read the post.
I'm sorry, the prose etta by Snorrius Thurlson, who is, you know, that's one of the classic sources of Norse myth.
Story of Sturlson, of course, is a Christian, but he starts out the prose etta by saying that the Norse gods are actually heroes from Troy who traveled North and became worshiped as gods by the people there.
So it's interesting that even even this Christians take on the origin of Norse paganism,
Connects it back to
the fall of Troy, right? He's connecting it back again to the Iliad history proper. Yeah, right.
History proper. Yeah. Yeah. It's interesting to see how these different, you know, the same
historical sources get used by very different cultures for different purposes. But it's always about
connecting it back. You know, where we are now is connected back to the this source. Right. And once
Rome conquered Greece.
Right, Greece is now part of the Roman Empire.
So those Greek stories, that story of the history of the Hellenic peoples becomes part of the story of the history of Rome.
Right. Right, which is one of the reasons, I got this is one of the things I've been studying a little bit is over the last year or two is Christian objects, you know, objects created by Christians in many cases by like monks.
within fully crystallized places, that include pagan imagery.
Right? So I mean, one of the...
classic examples is there's the 13th century, I think it's called the Healistod,
Stave Church, in Norway that includes images from the legend of Sigurd on the doorposts
on the outside of the church. But it's, you know, there aren't any pagans around probably
or not too many at that time. But the point is, is that this story, this history that is
the Norwegians, the Norse people, has now been incorporated into the Christian story of Norway.
that it's just simply part of that story now too.
They're not saying you should go ahead and worship those gods
that are people used to worship, but rather that these stories that make up the culture
of this people are now part of our, continue to be part of our story, but now
there in many cases reinterpreted, transformed in some ways,
extra commentary added, all that kind of stuff to incorporate it into that people's consciousness
that particular point in history.
Right. And to help redirect those people.
consciousness of themselves. Right? So you're no longer, you know, a Greek who's at the end of this Greek story. Right?
You're now a Greek who's part of this Roman story. Let's now continuing. Right.
And what are the places where we see this kind of thing still happening today is the whole idea of Western civilization.
Yeah, and Western Civ classes, right because it is not an
reading of history to start history with ancient Sumer and end it with the United States winning World War II.
There's not just a clear line that goes between those. That's not like a completely objective. Right. That's that's a process of a
civilization of a whole bunch of stories. Yeah, and I mean it's a selection of different people's radically different people's. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Right. I mean, and I think like especially
especially American culture and...
which is the result, the American culture as it now stands
is the result of numerous streams of immigration.
And this makes it easier for people to do that, right?
Like, you know, the story of the country my ancestors came from
is now part of my story, it's part of the American story,
and so forth. But again, it gets reinterpreted.
Like, so, for instance, you know, you could study
You could study whatever, like, you know, you being of Dutch ancestry, maybe.
of Lithuanian, we can study those places, we can understand those places, we can even understand
our particular four bears who were immigrants, but the story of those places went on without our
families. And so even though there may be a genetic link between us and that country, and even
though there may be some connections, you know, maybe quizinas passed down or maybe language,
although if you get enough generations that the language usually stops at some point.
Our story is not their story.
Their story has moved on without us.
Our story has moved on without them.
We no longer have the experience that those peoples have had.
Even though there is this common heritage,
it's no longer the same thing.
Because we're not participating in that
in their story anymore.
Right.
And that's why you get all of these
hyphenate Americans, right?
So I'm a Dutch American.
So the story starts.
in the Netherlands, but then it merges into this America story.
Right. And likewise with all the other various. Right.
Hi, Phoenix. Right. And so, but even more than just that sort of
master narrative, right, that still occasionally gets taught is history. In fact,
most popular level history and the history you're going to get at most, you know,
Oh.
junior high, high schools, elementary schools in the United States at least is this kind of history.
It's not really pretending to be objective, right? Right.
And but beyond even that sort of official narrative, there's also the fact that every group and even
every person has their own kind of functional phenomenological history, right? They have their own
story about who they are and the history of their people, their family.
who they are and that varies a lot.
It has nothing to do with what did
or didn't actually happen.
Right.
I mean, there's a gazillion things that have happened
to me in my life that I simply do not remember
because they weren't important to me to remember.
Right.
And I grew up, for example, in a Dutch community
in Southern California.
So the American Civil War is not part of my personal history.
Like, I don't really have...
any firm real connection to it. Right. I just I don't. Right. I now live in Louisiana.
Here are a lot of people that is part of their personal history. Right. Because I don't
deny that the American Civil War happened. Right. Right. It happened. But that fact is
not super relevant to who I am, where I came from, where I'm going in the future.
Interestingly, let's say your whole clan moves to Louisiana,
and eventually they have descendants,
and they have descendants,
then what can happen is that because they are participating
in Louisiana culture, Louisiana's history becomes much more
important to them, as I saw.
Like I'm interested in Emmaus, Pennsylvania history,
but there is zero record that I'm aware of
of anyone I was ever related to,
ever living here before me.
But if you're kids and
and Greg can stay there.
Right.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And so, in a lot of cases, what makes that, what helps craft, shall we say, that functional
history is actually ritual activity, right?
So the church example of this, right, is that what we say, blessed are, that we've got
of our fathers.
We're talking about Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.
We're calling them up.
fathers, right? Doesn't matter if you're not Jewish. Doesn't matter if you're not even from a
Semitic people group, right? They have become your fathers because that has become your history. That's
why Saint Paul can writing to the church at Corinth in a chapter where he's pointed out that they
all used to worship idols. So he's talking to Gentiles. He could say, remember our fathers were all
baptized into Moses.
Right. So this is not just a theological point, right? This is not some kind of replacement
theology. This is not some kind of weird anti-semitism. This is how functional history works.
Right. And it worked that way in the Old Testament. Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob were Ruth's
for others, even though she was a Moabite.
And Caleb, even though he was a kittasite.
Right, I mean, as Ruth said,
your people will be my people,
your God will be my God.
That's exactly what she's saying
is that it becomes hers
as a result of her participation in that people.
Right, and this still kind of takes place
on a secular level as well,
although it's also through ritual activity.
Right.
in natural
When you're naturalized into a new country, you move to another country and you become a citizen there. There's a process you go through and there's usually some kind of oath-taking involved.
There's some kind of ritual ceremony involved where you become a part of that people.
It doesn't matter where you were born and where you grew up, now you are part of that people
and the history of that people now becomes your history.
Yep, exactly.
You are a part of that.
Yeah, so that's ancient history.
That's the way history used to be, right?
Yes, that's ancient ancient history.
Or pre-modern history in many ways.
Just simply pre-modern history.
Yeah, yeah, pre-modern history.
And so then our German friends come along
and decide that history should be a vissen shaft.
Vissen shaft.
about you're all asking yourself what exactly does is
words, visten shop to mean.
That's right. It's time for Father Andrew's etymology corner and have to credit listeners
slash catechumin Chris Hoyle who sent that little jingle in for us and that is his two-year-old
daughter Eleanor at the end. That is not a simulated baby sound. That's real. So yes, the
The babies were harmed in the...
the making of this channel.
No, that was sheer unmitigated joy.
So just which is that is the way I feel about etymology.
So this and soft, right, to German word, literally, if you want to pull it out from its roots,
it means knowledge making.
So that this and part comes from the Germanic root, we-ton, w-i-t-a-n, which means to know.
And that actually comes from a proto-indo-Europe-
in root, I'm not sure if I'm pronouncing this correctly,
Wade, W-E-Y-D, which means to see.
And actually is the origin of our word video
and stuff like this, right?
But so in Old English, Weetan generally meant to know,
but it actually more specifically means to be aware of,
to be aware of.
That's how it's related to the Indo-European word to see, right?
And then this is where we get the modern English word,
wise and also wit and wizard.
A wizard is...
an old is a guy who knows things. It's not a guy who does magical tricks. So these are
all these are all words that are connected in English. Vistenschaft is a technical term
in German academia, right? And usually the word gets translated into English as science.
Simply as science, Vistenschaft means science. But when it is used in English, often it gets
used in an untranslated way, we just simply see
Vistenshoft, as you did.
When it gets used in English that way, we're talking about 19th century German academia.
That's exactly what it all is.
All it is.
That, ladies and gentlemen, is the etymology of Vistenshoft as it gets used in English.
It's emolitude with Father Andrew.
There you are.
I love those little jingles for this segment.
Thank you, Chris Hoyle.
very 80
synth pop. Isn't it? Yeah. Mark Mothers-Bommé Sue but we'll go on. So now everybody knows
what Vizenshoft is. Yes. So this is the idea that history is a sort of science. Right? So
So historical inquiry, historical methodology shifts to this kind of science.
scientific or quasi-scientific approach, right? Meaning
Obviously you can't conduct experiments, but you gather evidence you gather historical evidence
From that historical evidence you form a hypothesis
That explains as best you can the evidence you have
And then
You're kind of at an impasse is is the problem because
There's not really a good way to test that hypothesis because someone else could come along
and construct a totally different hypothesis based on the same evidence.
So if you get lucky and you're doing archaeology and you find some more evidence that might
help prove or help disprove your hypothesis.
But barring that, this is why you get a lot of debates talking about, for example, explanatory
power.
Like, which one of these hypotheses?
is these best explains the evidence or explains more of the evidence.
And it becomes sort of a fine debate, right?
And the further you go back in history, the more difficult it is because the less
evidence you have.
Right. And then you can, you know, dig up one thing from some forgotten city
and then that changes everything.
Hypothetically, yes,
aesthetically, because you also get things like, okay, we all agree that King David
didn't exist right but it didn't exist right but it didn't exist right but it didn't
just like King Arthur. It was like, yeah, yeah, we all agree. It's called a guild.
Okay, we found the subscription that mentions his name.
So then you get the guy, you know, King Arthur was real, by the way. Yeah. The guys,
the guys who have made their career arguing he didn't exist, right? Now come out with articles
like, well, that doesn't say, uh, uh, bait, deweed, uh, that says bait, dode, says, uh,
So how's the David it's house of the water bucket and then
It's a real example. It is a real example. I knew it. And then constructed a elaborate argument
for why Israel would be called the House of the Water Bucket. Wow. Right. But again, it's a hypothesis.
Right? Like, sure. Right. Uh, explanatory power. So. And, uh, everybody would have known better
if they just paid attention to Aristotle.
Hmm.
Which is a quote you dropped.
been a lot of places. Yeah, right. So Aristotle, all the way back in the four century BC,
pointed out that history is always a matter of doxa, which means an opinion.
Opinion. Yeah, I wasn't going to throw out the etymology thing for that, for everybody.
But yeah, it does mean opinion, or I mean, sometimes can mean teaching, but it's real
basis is opinion. It's related to
like reputation and this is also why it means glory. Because the glory is is what surrounds
and is set about a person or a thing or whatever the Voksa.
Yeah, so not only is later you know not mean work of the people, but orthodoxy does not
mean right glory or right worship. Right opinion. Anyway.
Yeah, yeah, and that kind of and that cover needs it seems it seems any
And it's the basis of a word dogma too, actually, again, from that it seems because it's
seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us.
That's where that usage comes for dogma.
And dacetism is the heresy that Christ just seemed to be a man.
He just appeared as a man, but it was not actually right.
But seeming doesn't necessarily mean deception.
No, right.
You can have a right opinion.
Yes, yeah.
You can say it seems to me.
someone says it seems to me they're not saying well I imagine
And like they're not saying, I think that I'm believing in illusion, they're saying this
is how I understand it.
This is how it seems to me.
Right.
And so the point Aristotle is making what he says that, that it's the matter of opinion,
is that's as opposed to the type of knowledge that he describes as epistemi, which is
usually translated also science.
But it's a kind of knowledge that could be demonstrated.
So if I say to you two plus two weeks.
four and you're dubious, right? I can get two apples and then another two apples and show you,
right? Right. And you will see, oh yes, your statement was correct two plus two equals four.
And if I say to you, if you had a time machine and you went back and time and killed William Howard
taft. You would prevent the Russian Revolution and at least one of the world wars, right?
There's no way for me to demonstrate that to you.
I can't prove that to you.
Right, because you can't do controlled experiments
on history.
Right.
I can't lay out math to prove that.
I can make an argument, but that argument is just
going to be an argument for my opinion.
Right.
So that's the difference there.
As inside.
As a side.
Go ahead, go ahead, go ahead.
Okay, aside from our atheist friends.
Right. You know who you are. This is one of the biggest misunderstandings in popular
Christian and anti-Christian apologetic stuff. Right. People talk about Thomas Aquinas
and his proofs for the existence of God. And they talk about them as if Thomas Aquinas
ever met an atheist in his life. Right? First of all,
And that when he met that atheist, these were his five sure fire ways to prove the on a shadow of a doubt that God exists
Which is also not what they're about, right?
So what Aquinas was doing what Thomas was doing he had read Aristotle
right
And so he was trying to prove that theology as a discipline is not a matter of opinion
that it's a matter of epistemia.
It's a matter of science, right?
And so these are his demonstrations, right?
These are his logical demonstrations of the existence of God to show that theology is
certain knowledge and not purely the subject of opinion.
Right.
That's what he's doing.
You could disagree with him, right?
On all of them if you want to, right?
he never claimed here here's the surefire way
prove to it atheist that God exists, right?
That's not at all what it was about.
It was about what type of knowledge theology is.
Yeah, and I mean, the thing that occurs to me
is that even attempts to,
like our modern sense of history,
like we can't just jump out of the way
that most people do history now and say,
I'm not gonna do that anymore, right?
But it's even that, right?
Like I'm looking at my bookshelf right now,
and I have a bunch of history books on there.
And most of them are doing this,
this later variety of history.
Right? But even that, you know, so when Stephen Runseman writes his his his histories about the crusades or you know, the fall of Constance and Opal, this kind of thing, he's making selections based on things that he's found or things he's usually read.
and creating a narrative based on that.
It's not a videotape of everything that happened.
It's still making a selection, it's still creating a narrative.
There's still no way around the, it seems to me.
There's just no way around.
You cannot escape that.
And I think part of our modern tension is that, in many cases, we're not aware that we're
doing that.
Although, I mean, we're going to get to that about how that awareness has come, right?
Yeah.
But that we don't realize that it's actually the way we think what we think we're doing
is in fact intention with what we really are doing.
That's the problem.
Since there's this
We think we're doing science, but we're actually not. We're doing story. That's what we're doing. Which modern is not bad.
Modernism makes this pretense to objectivity. Right. Right.
We're not saying they succeeded being objective. Modernism succeeded being objective, but they make a pretense to it.
Before they did not make a pretense to it. Right. There was no idea that that was even a...
There was no idea that any word was there subjective objective was
anything anybody was thinking about, right? Right. So there's this pretense to objectivity and
that we're going to find we're going to find what really happened. Right. We're going to uncover it.
And so that means a text, no matter what kind of text we're talking about. But this includes the
Bible relevant to what we're talking about tonight. The Bible now is not a history to be incorporated
into your history. The Bible is now a piece of evidence.
It's now an artifact to be weighed against other pieces of evidence.
And what really happened lays somewhere back behind it.
Right?
And this is just one sort of perspective on it.
And so the kind of, again, it's the pre-tensed objectivity.
What really happened back behind there
isn't related to any particular group of people.
It claims to be
the view from nowhere, right? Like there is no perspective, they claim. Right? This is purely objective.
There is no viewpoint, no standpoint, no observer. Right? This is just how it is. Yeah. The tail
without the teller as if that's actually possible. Yeah. Yeah. So now we're going to get back
specifically debilical interpretation because uh...
After this starts in Europe, right?
And there's this transition.
So in the 17th and 18th century,
the early modern period,
what you get is,
you get people still treating the Bible
as a true account, right?
As a true historical account,
as these things are starting to shift.
But they want to try to dematologize it,
kind of naturalize it, right?
So they're going to say the story of
Christ walking on the water to the disciples. Well, that's a true account. But what really
happened was that Jesus was walking on this sand bar that they couldn't see. Right. Right.
He just he could see the sand bar. Right. So we've got to preserve the account. But we
also don't want to accept anything supernatural. Yeah. Once you get to the late 18th and into
the 19th century, it's just like, yeah, that never happened. Right. The story itself is
just a fabricate.
Right. Right. It's just a story. Right. And you treat it as a, you treat it as a piece of evidence. And in this case, it's not a very good piece of evidence because it's got this stuff supernatural stuff in it. Right.
Which, yeah.
Yeah.
And so it gets treated like the epic of Gilgamesh or the Anuoli, or Greek myths, or whatever. Right. Right.
And I mean, then it only makes sense, then, that a number of committed Christians are going to say, wait a minute.
Naha!
This happened. The Bible is true. Right. And that plays out in a particular set of debates. Right. Right. And it starts because this, this kind of history and then resulting in this approach to the Bible comes to completely dominate European universities.
And this is a period of time as we get toward the end of the 19th moving toward the 20th century.
This is a time when what we now call the Ivy League School.
right like the the major universities a lot of their
their professors and instructors are being educated at
these European universities right right we sometimes
you know I know we have a lot of listeners who aren't in the
United States but we in the United States are very full of
ourselves that we like to forget that before World War 2 we
were still kind of a backwater it's only post World War 2
that like Britain receded and the US became the major
way around the
world stage. Well, don't worry, I'm sure we're hit for backwater status again sometimes.
So, oh, no doubt. But, but so these things that we think of as these major Ivy League
school, right, were not considered the great institutions of higher learning for the
world, right? Right. Right. Right. Are American students who had real promise they went to
Europe to study. And so some of these folks...
We'll throw a shout out to Jane Grisha, Machen.
We're educated over there.
We're educated in this kind of modernist approach to the Bible.
But because they were actual Christians,
I'll be a Protestant, right?
They were horrified.
Right?
They saw where this was leading.
Right.
They saw where this was going.
Because it starts out well enough like,
well, hey, some of the supernatural stuff
of the Bible is kind of goofy.
I can't believe it.
but then it moves to life.
I don't know about this virgin birthing.
I don't know about this Jesus being God thing.
Yeah.
Right.
And it sort of progresses until there's less and less left, not just of the Bible, but of
Christianity.
Right.
Isn't there a very famous cartoon I recall, which is depicted as a stairway where, you know,
gradually, you know, I think it was called the descent into modernism or something like
that.
where they start taking...
off core beliefs of Christianity and then that eventually leads you down into the bottom
which I think is like unbelief or something. I'm not looking at it right now. But yeah,
I mean, there's an illustration of this reaction that these people have.
I'm trying to remember there's a 20th century saint who actually talked about this,
say Orthodox church. And what I remember about is he talked about how ironic it was because most
of these institutions, especially once in Germany, were Protestant institutions.
Hmm. Oh yeah, here. I was gonna say I found the I found the cartoon. Yeah, go ahead. Go ahead. Yeah
It's called the descent of the modernists
Yeah, and it starts out like in the top step you've got Christianity and the next step down is the Bible is not infallible and then
Man not made in God's image then no miracles then no virgin birth and no deity no atonement
No resurrection agnosticism at the bottom is atheism
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, the 20th century Orthodox saint said how ironic it was at these Protestant institutions in northern Europe that the Protestant movement had laid down the scriptures as the foundation for everything they were going to do and then turn around and undermine their own foundation.
Hmm.
So the whole thing started to collapse.
But so, folks in America kind of saw this coming
and saw this happen.
It did not want American institutions like Old Princeton to go the way of European institutions
even though they eventually did.
That's it rather quickly.
But and so they set out to put a stop to this and the movement that ensued to debate against
the modernists was led by a group who wrote these tracts on what they considered to be the
the most important.
the important aspects of the Christian faith.
So there are tracks on things like the Virgin birth,
the deity of Christ, the whole Trinity, right?
These tracks, these are...
Fundamentals.
From a Protestant perspective,
those were eventually collected as the fundamentals.
Right.
I mean, this is the origin of the word fundamentalism.
Those were the fundamentalists.
Yeah, exactly.
It did not mean everybody,
someone who is more serious about religion than I am
and probably has a gun.
That's not what I-
anything with violence? No, or extremism. Right.
Originally, originally, it was it was a it was simply a small O orthodoxy.
Does, you know, designed to say these are the non-negotiables that you have to believe in or to be
are kind of Christian. And for most of the first half of the 20th century, there were a lot of people
who would proudly call themselves in major Protestant denominations of the US proudly call themselves
even gelical fundamentalists.
Oh sure. I mean, I mean...
was no pejorative attached to that word.
Yeah, no, I recall in the 70s and 80s,
that was still being used and no one,
and it was not, that I'm aware of,
it was not being used as a pejorative.
Well, you were hanging out with a bunch of crazy stuff.
I, well,
I was.
No, I mean, it was, it was,
it was, it was a label that a lot people used,
and it just meant we're really used.
Yeah, we put out themselves.
Yeah, they would put on themselves, yeah.
Yeah.
And so this is, this period,
late 19.
20th century is referred to as the modernist fundamentalist controversy or the modernist fundamentalist debate the scope's monkey trial and all that stuff comes out of this
and
coming to it from an orthodox perspective there's a basic problem with both sides.
Right. And that's that both sides share a fundamental presupposition.
Both of them are accepting this modernist view of history.
Right because the fundamentalists did not reject that modernist view of history
Right, they accepted it. They just insisted that that's what the Bible was
Right, and so it could line up you could you could demonstrate the truth of the Bible using empirical
Scientific means right, I mean, and this is the birth of kind of modern Christian
archaeology biblical archaeology. Yes, that's where the starts and
And it's a cliche.
literature now to talk about these people who during this period went out with a Bible in
one hand and a spade in the other to dig and try and prove. That prove that everything is
objectively true, that the Old Testament is written from no perspective, which is clearly
a fool's errand. But to any reader, it's definitely from a perspective. But so this has
a number of bad effects.
Right?
Even on the conservative side, I mean the negative effects on the modernist side, we've
already kind of mentioned, right?
We already mentioned that.
That's problematic.
But even on the fundamentalist or the conservative side, since nobody likes that term anymore,
this led to the marginalization of a lot of non-history parts of the Bible.
Right.
No one says, are the Psalms objectively true?
Proverbs.
song of song.
ecclesiasties, even the profits, right?
With a few exceptions of particular,
you know, particular hot button passages in some of the profits.
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, and I was just going to say that the fun flip side is
then how this approach gets used on the book of Revelation.
Because there it's not about trying to dig stuff up to prove that it's true.
Now it's about trying to find pieces of evidence in the moment that we're in
that proves...
that the things said in the book of Revelation are about to happen in the way that I think
that they are. So I mean, it works in both ends, coming and going.
It's being interpreted as future positivist history.
Right.
Yeah.
And then you also get, so once you say, no, this is objective.
This is what really happened, perspective from nowhere.
You create all these problems for yourself.
Right. So if you say that about the gospels, oh no, right? Like what do we do now?
The gospels have some of these events at different orders
Right and oh no, here there's one blind man and here. There's two blind men. Oh here
There's two angels inside the tomb and one here's there's one outside the tomb and here's this right
and
you know
Is it the late date of the Exodus is the early date?
of the Exodus is the even earlier date of the accident, right? What date of the Exodus happened?
And you know, how long is a day in Genesis one and how old is the earth and etc. etc.
All these things that I say put me to sleep, right? Because because they're not interesting to me
because I don't share that presupposition. Right? I don't share the presupposition
that the Bible is modernist.
history, right? I don't share this presupposition that the book of Exodus was written with any
intent to help me figure out what year it happened. Right. Right. And I mean, I think the sort
of caveat that I would add to all of the foregoing is to say, at least on my part, I don't
know how you feel about this because we didn't talk about this, is to say that the methodology
of gathering together evidence and trying to...
create narratives out of that, whether it's a scientific narrative about chemical processes,
or it's about, like, by no means are we saying that you shouldn't do archaeology, right?
Or that you shouldn't do experiments. It's just that to take that methodological frame and put
it onto the Bible is super problematic. If you're trying to understand the purpose of the Bible,
and especially as a Christian.
what is the purpose of the Bible in my life? Right? I don't know how you would,
whether you would agree with that or not. Right. Well, let's say, let's say tomorrow,
some industrious person is digging out the Sinai desert and I'm covering something that proves
beyond a shadow of a doubt that the Exodus happens. Right? And he goes on all the social media,
it says, check made atheists. How many atheists do you think are going to be convinced to become
Christians based on that.
Right. My estimate would be zero. Yeah. Right. Right. Like that's not a thing. Right. That's not that's not how this works. Right. Yeah. So I mean, yes.
conservative evangelicals also have to publish journal articles and write dissertations.
This is a good way to find a topic, find an apparent contradiction.
and have at it, right?
But how productive it is for the purposes of the spiritual life,
the church, people finding their salvation,
is an open question.
I'll say polite.
Right.
So yeah, so in both,
the modernist or what comes to be called liberalism,
Oh, but the...
liberal theological approach. You have this positive history that stands behind the Bible
in fundamentalism or as it comes with conservatism, right, conservative theology. You have the Bible
is itself positivist history but both of those are modernisms. Right. Right. I don't know if I've
denunciated this this clearly on the show. So I will now send your angry cards and letters to
to Father Andrew. Yes, I will read them.
The younger earth creationism is modernism.
Amen.
There you go.
But we are still going to the arc experience though, right?
No.
Oh, man, we are not.
You're welcome to.
But you'll have to find sharing that experience with me.
I do have to find someone to go see that with.
Cause I love, I don't know.
There's something about the kits of that part of the religious world
that I just...
I'm super into.
So yeah, yeah, he's building a tower of Babel now too, which I know was such a great idea the first time
Exactly it's like when they said they were making a replica of the Titanic to sail across the Atlantic for the
anniversary like that at that anniversary I was like
Really
It's gonna be different this time. Yeah, yeah
Yeah.
Okay, so we've set ourselves up.
So I mean, that kind of takes us...
into most, you know, much of the 20th century. And is this still the frame
the lot of the world still thinks in?
There's still a modernist around. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, there's still the ones
largely publishing textbooks and stuff. And, you know, that kind of thing. But
there's another shift that occurred within the 20th century, which has made this
all even more problematic, right? Or at least confusing. Yeah. Yeah. And that's
postmodernism.
Yeah, or to be more specific post structuralism. Yeah. Yeah.
And I know I know I know this is going to be a very long first half everybody,
but we really, we need to set all this up to be able to give you this stuff
in the second. If you complain about how long this show is,
you're not going to have a good time with this show. And you must be new here.
You need, yeah, you need to just settle in. Right. Right.
I mean, orthodox church services, same thing. Holy week's coming up, man.
Exactly. You're into the duration.
So yes, post.
structuralism. I remember first hearing about this when I was an undergrad doing English literature study.
Yeah. Well the word postmodern gets thrown around so much now that it gets applied to
everything. Yes. Right. We're postmodern. Various forms of modernism. Pre-anti postmodern
post-modern modernism.
The ultimate...
Pre-anti-punultimate...
No, I don't know.
Yeah.
And we're not going to talk about it tonight, but believe it or not, there is such a thing as meta-modernism.
But anyway, so they haven't gotten too much of a hold of the Bible yet.
So postmodernism is basically a continuation of the modernist move that starts with
Because as the Bible was demoted
Yeah, to a piece of evidence, right, or a source, right, by the modernist, it then comes
to be approached with a hermeneutic of suspicion, right?
So it's not just that, well, this is one version of the story or one perspective on events,
but this is an official narrative designed to cover up what was actually going on.
Yeah.
So if you read in Exodus about the dedication of the
first born at the tabernacle. Clearly, this is covering up the fact that the
ancient Israelites sacrificed their children to Yahweh, the God of Israel. I mean,
clearly, yeah, obviously, right? Based on, you know, not much, but other than this,
again, this hereditary was sufficient, right? That if this is the official story,
Right. Right. Then the truth must be something different and we try to read motives.
to whoever we think wrote the official story, like the priestly cast or what have you,
in order to disclose.
So then it moves on from there, essentially you end up in a situation where you just have
perspectives now.
Right.
It takes all the bias.
whatever, whatever quote unquote really happened become sort of inaccessible.
So there are actually ways in which post-structuralism is helpful.
Right, and other ways that it's not.
Right, definitely ways it's not.
Right, right.
So one way it's helpful is it does take seriously as we've quoted Nagel, not just the
bat thing, but there's no view from nowhere.
Right?
That every author, every source, every, maybe not a piece of physical archaeological
electrical evidence but the
person who finds it and the person who interprets it, they all have a perspective, they all have
biases, they all come from a culture, right? And so there's no objective, anything, right,
accessible to us, right? And that gets taken seriously. So that modernist pretense that
was always a fake pretense to objectivity kind of gets killed. Right. And I'm saying,
that's a good, that's a good thing. Killing that pretense. Yeah. Every, every tail has a
there is no escape from that.
Right. And another good part is the idea that, relatedly, the person who's reading the
Bible, the person who's actually reading, is part of the reading of the Bible.
Right. They're not receiving an objective Bible. Like when they come to it, you're coming
to it with your knowledge of language, you're coming to it with your personal opinions
about things that might remind you of something that happened to in your life.
you're coming to it with the fact that you're receiving this probably in translation,
but even if you're reading it and, you know, one of the original languages,
you learned Greek or Hebrew from somebody who taught it to you in a particular way.
You have a lexicon written by somebody who has their own take. Like, like, there's,
just, you probably heard sermons in your life and that's going to bring
context to your reading. I could just go on and on. There's no
around the human participation in the reading of the Bible and that when you receive it then
that comes along with it. There's just no way out of that, right?
Right. And since we're ticket people off tonight, and I say this, honestly, I say this
with love to our Protestant friends. I think one of the reasons Solar Script
is problematic is that we don't have access to the Bible outside of our experience of reading the Bible.
Right.
Like, you know, I say an infallible text requires an infallible interpreter.
Is it kind of another way of looking at that?
Right. And so when I read it, right, I am bringing my subjectivity into the mix.
Yeah, and so
So unless there's some way to access the infallible text without bringing my subjectivity into
the mix, it becomes difficult to see how that text can serve as an objective standard of
truth.
Right.
Yep.
But I will leave it at that.
Now, you probably have guessed that and we've implied any number of bad things about this.
Right?
Yes.
But ultimately...
to sum it up, you end up with a situation where texts can mean anything and therefore
end up meaning nothing.
Right.
There's no meaning you can isolate.
There's just a thousand perspectives that there's no way to mediate between them because
there's no access to the reality behind it.
And so, they can mean anything.
Nothing is nothing.
Yeah.
There is
is no communication happening ever.
It's sort of the, yeah.
Yeah, and that results in you end up with practices
like you'll find this in biblical studies
and journal articles, if you read JBL,
where you find readings of texts against the grain.
Right, so classic real example of this,
reading the book of Ezekiel from the perspective
of the witches he condemns.
Right? So you're deliberately, you are reading it from the opposite perspective of what
you intend of what the text intended. Right. Right. So, um, and this, this is why, this
is why you end up in this. It can mean anything or nothing place. Right? Because if you could
read a text, it's meaning the exact opposite of what it says, then you could read it any
which way.
Yeah, exactly.
And it's just whatever meaning you give it.
Right.
And the meaning is just, now, to be fair, right,
this isn't just unnewanced, right.
So, proponents of this would say meaning arises within the interaction between your subjectivity and the text,
which is also subjective.
Right.
But it's all subjectivity.
therefore the meaning that arises from that encounter between you and the tech.
is just a meaning for you. Right. And and that's not entirely invalid in the sense that this happens.
Yeah, sure. Right. Like yeah. Yeah. I've published a couple books occasionally I get an email from
somebody who says, oh, this thing you said here was so important to me. It's wonderful. Really changed
how I think about this and what they tell me, I have no idea how they got that out of my book.
I'm sorry.
right? Right. You know, usually we get the emails saying, you know, I can't believe
you said x, y and z. And again, we're saying, I have no idea how they got that out of
it. Right. But in that positive case, right? Now I don't write back to that person to say,
no, you're wrong. That's not right. Right. Right. Like I think that's great. But that
is a case where this has happened. Right. They and their subjectivity, they had things
going on in their life. They come from a background. They're in a situation that I
I didn't foresee.
And so something in my book that came from my subjectivity spoke to something in their
subjectivity and produced a good result. The result's good. Great, right? So they're
not totally all wet with this. Yeah, I mean, the point where it becomes kind of a freaky
feedback loop, though, is when someone derives something within their subjectivity and then
tells everybody else that that's how it, that's what it is. That's how it, you know, that's
what it really means. You have to accept my subject.
reading of this now. Right. Or even if they don't do that, right, is that what that does is it
takes meaning and atomizes it. Yeah. Right. So we're no longer a community that has this story
as part of our shared history where a group of individuals, each of whom in our own subjectivity,
has a particular connection to this story that's completely independent and might be the opposite of
the person to my left.
Yeah.
Right.
And so you can't build community based on that.
Uh, and you know, Christ actually exists.
Yeah.
Right.
And we believe you could have, as orthodox Christians,
you could have personal encounter with him,
not just read about him, right.
Um, and so there's sort of no room for that in this
just subjectivity of text, right.
So it's a way of talking about people reading Moby Dick.
Okay, I read Moby Dick.
And, you know, because I read Moby Dick,
I now understand I can't destroy the enterprise
just to stop the board, right?
Well, I mean, that is what a particular meaning, right?
For one person's subjectivity.
That's an important lesson though.
But Herman Melville did not have that in mind.
No, right at all.
Would he wrote Moby Dick?
So, right, for so for that kind of situation,
yes, it is descriptive.
but the Bible
as we're going to continue to talk about tonight has a particular relationship to a particular community.
Yeah, right. That that and so functions differently than just a book. Yeah, even at or a history book.
Right. Right. You also then get what could be described as standpoint epistemology,
which is the idea that because everybody's reading just from their own perspective,
right it's their own subjectivity then
And, you know, if we're all aware of that and we all agree to that, then I have to introduce
my meaning from the text by stating my standpoint or bias.
So, you know, as a Gen X Dutch American from Southern California, this text speaks to
be this way. Right.
And we've all heard as a blank, right?
Done it all right.
Right.
Yeah.
It's it's it's it's it's appeal to authority.
But it's this inaccessible.
Inaccessible authority.
Right.
Well, you're not me.
And so therefore you just can't get this.
Right.
You don't have this knowledge because you don't share my experiences as a fill in the blank.
Therefore, this is inaccessible to you and you just have to trust me.
Right.
I mean, because I
the authority of experience.
Yeah, you know, up to the point where someone says,
you just have to trust me.
I'm like, well, okay, it's true.
I don't have your experiences and I'm not you.
But if this is something that we're going to be sharing,
then that's just not acceptable.
Right. You know, right.
Especially if you're trying to put it on me in some way.
I can't just say, yes, yes, it's true.
I'm not whatever it is you are.
Therefore, you're the the expert period.
Right. And and I know a lot of people out there.
because I have some idea of the makeup of our audience. A lot of people on there now are thinking of
like identity politics. And that is an example of standpoint of epistemology. But this same way of
thinking manifests itself on the more, quote unquote conservative side too, with appeals to the
the Holy Spirit, holiness, virtue, possession of the phronium of the fathers, right?
Whatever.
someone wants to claim, right?
A claim to spiritual experience
or the Holy Spirit acting in their life, right?
That allows them, again, to understand the text
in a way that you cannot.
It's an appeal to authority
that you can't interact with, right?
They're personal spiritual experience
rather than some kind of secular identity.
Yeah, who was it?
Who was it that had a footnote that said,
you know, this was revealed to me in a dream?
I'm trying to remember who that was.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But I mean, that's real. That's a real thing. People like, you know, I have this,
like you're just going to have to go with me on this. Yeah. You know, I have this personal
experience or personal identity, whatever. And therefore I spend a lot of time in prayer.
The Holy Spirit is telling me this. Yeah. Right. And there's no way to counter argue that
with the person, right?
Right.
They're claiming experience.
that you don't share, and so there's no, right.
And so that ends up creating sort of in groups and out groups.
Right, exactly.
Right.
In this either in the sort of secular identity,
politics sense, or in a kind of nostic sense,
among more conservative religious communities,
where there are these enlightened people
who are in the nose spiritually,
and then these other spiritual roles
who don't know anything.
and
that are just supposed to
trust right the the illuminated ones. Right and so now we've talked about how bad
everything is. Right? This is really this is really all this bleakness. This is the world of
biblical studies. Now I know there's a few of you out there who are like, wow I like listening to
Lord of Spirits. I want to go get a PhD in biblical studies like Father Stephen did. Well maybe I've
I've talked to some of you out of it.
But not every school is pushing this, right?
But this is the landscape, right?
This is the landscape out there.
And we can kind of boil it down and summarize it to
all of it, whether it's a liberal, conservative,
modernist, postmodernist, right?
Which ever part of whatever spectrum you want to talk about.
We can kind of boil this down to the idea that
all of this modernism, postmodernism,
views the Bible as making claims.
Yeah.
Alright, the b-
So I will make truth claims.
Right. So we have to check them and see if they're true or false.
Right. And those truth claims are either it's they're making a truth claim and we need to verify scientifically that this truth claim is scientifically accurate.
Or in the more postmodern thing, it's this is making truth claims, but that's just from this one perspective.
So we need to isolate that perspective and give equal voice to all the other perspectives.
But either way it's making claims. It's asserting something. There's four
or power being exercised.
Right.
And so, and this is what leads to these things.
So, if you read the measurements of Noah's Ark, speaking of the Ark encounter, right,
those measures, you say, the Bible is making a claim that Noah's Ark had these exact
dimensions.
Right.
and you get can have...
telling you well if that's not true then you just throw the Bible and Christianity in the garbage can.
Right. Right. That becomes the basis. Exactly those dimensions. Right. Right. Because it's making a claim
and right. And so that's sort of the the unnewanced version of this. Right. Right. Most people
Folks are more nuanced that our friend can have.
People like Friend of the Show, Bart Erman.
And so he's more on the, what we might call the liberal side, I guess, of that.
But also you find more nuanced people on the conservative side, right, who will separate
out different types of claims.
They don't question whether the Bible's making claims.
They're still using this modern or postmodern approach that the Bible makes claims.
the separate out, right? Historical claims from like
scientific claims. And so they'll say for example, when the Bible speaks as if the sun goes
around the earth, it's not making that as a claim. That as it count as a claim. So it's
okay that that's not accurate scientifically, right? But those same folks will then say
that any historical data in the Bible is a claim.
Right.
And so, Fred, the show barterman, if I prove these historical claims untrue, that throw
Christianity in the dumpster, and the response to him is, no, I'm going to prove all of those
historical claims true.
Right?
So, the nuance folks will say, the Bible is not a science textbook, and I agree with them.
The Bible is also not a history textbook.
Right.
It's not trying to say things about history that it's not trying to say about.
It's not trying to do either thing. That's not its purpose.
Right. It's not its purpose.
Right. And the Bible is not a modern book making claims.
Right.
It's telling a story.
Exactly.
The story of a people.
To which you are invited to belong.
Exactly.
Okay, good night.
No, there is more to say.
There's two more halves.
That's right. But before we say it,
We're gonna go ahead and take a short break
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have...
have questions about Orthodox Christianity that you can't trust strangers in internet
forums to answer.
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place to send your interested
friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox Church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodge.
I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lucas.
I serve in the Orthodox Church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook.
I serve in the Greek Orthodox...
Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries
and a priest of the Antioch in Archdiocese.
And where the Orthodox Intro Team?
If you're looking for a first stop online
to getting introduction to the Orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions
from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy,
a place to send your friends
and not just toss them into the chaos of the Internet,
a place to get help finding an Orthodox parish
and get
plugged into an actual Orthodox community, then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
Orthodoxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox enramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's orthroxintro.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
We're talking about biblical interpretation.
It's a big old methodology episode.
Not a lot to dig up out of the desert for this one.
So the show is you, the commercial is.
you. I know. Are you just like a full on one man band now? I don't know. I mean, it wasn't just me
in the commercial though. I say it was a community, an interpretive community. Like if I switch over
to the music channel right now, will you be chanting? No, no, no. There are no recordings of me singing
that I'm aware of. Okay, I was gonna say somebody. It's somebody. Yes, something. I think that someone
did hold up their phone during a service one point but right so
But yes, we just paid to the very bleak landscape of, you know, how we got to where we are in terms of biblical interpretation.
So, but there's a lot, there's more to say on this, right? So like the implications of where we are now, right?
You know, this all, this all implies a certain methodology.
So we're going to talk in this half about the methodology that's implied by everything we just talked about and then
then make a turn to talk about the kind of methodology that we're employing on this
show.
And that we believe is very much the methodology of the way that the Bible is read in the
Orthodox Church and by the Orthodox Church, for the Orthodox Church.
All right, so having said all that, the Bible is in a modern book making claims.
So where are we now?
there will eventually be light at the end of this tunnel.
Yes, yes, we like episodes and then a relative the high note.
But, but we've, we've still got a little more tunnel.
Alas, incredibly.
So, yes, so so much for history, right?
And, and we need to spend that much time on it because this is frankly the
biggest problem right now to even coming to
interpretation is that, again, this modern view of history has become the predominant lens through which the scriptures are read.
And it's causing us to miss sort of everything in port. Right? So if the Bible isn't making claims scientific or historical.
right and we're talking about the problem with those kind of approaches and
getting locked in those debates.
is that you miss like actual meaning, right? And we talked about how meaning isn't just this
individualized, completely subjective thing, right? Now, we have to kind of turn to how do you
figure out what that is, right? Right. And actual harmonutics per se. Yes. Yeah.
harmonutics, not to be confused with Herman's head, the fine Fox television show of the early
a bit 90s. Nor with Herman Yudic.
the cousin, I believe, of Father Stephen Yudix.
Is that a real person?
I think it might be.
Or I just, I remember, no, I remember being mentioned, no, I remember being mentioned by
our common scripture professor at St. T. Cots.
Dr. Mary Ford, I think she made a reference to Herman Yudix, but I think that's the real person.
She might have been telling you that joke.
She might have, but I think it's not a dad.
That's true.
Yeah.
So.
So we have to sort of come at this from the perspective of presuppositions too, right?
Because, again, coming out of this modern and postmodern milieu, people often have an
idea that any given verse or passage or whatever unit of scripture we want to talk about
has a meaning.
Yeah, a single
meaning. Yeah, we get this question every so often. It shows up in our group too. You know,
what's the orthodox interpretation of this verse? Yeah. Right. Which I mean, I get what
I get that, you know, but we need to we need to kind of let go of that addiction. Right.
And so that that could be meant in either a modernist or a postmodernist sense, right? Yeah.
Right. In a postmodernist sense, it could be, well, what's the orthodox perspective on
to compare to the Roman Catholic.
and Protestant. Right. What's you guys take perspective on this? Or it could be from the
modernist perspective of what has the Orthodox Church historically said this verse means
like objectively, the meaning that lies behind the text, right? The same way that history sort
of lays behind the text, right? In that modernist sense. But so just to sort of problematize the
the modern version of that.
We've already kind of...
problematized to the post-modern version of that. But the modern version of that, the idea that
you come to the text, you engage in some sort of process and you come to that meaning that lies
behind it, right? I guess I'm not good. Right? The analogy old biblical interpreters used to
use was kernel and husk. There's this kernel of meaning and you have to sort of extract it from
from the husk.
Right, so.
Bye.
by getting into grammar and all these sort of things.
But so if we take that approach,
where the meaning lies somewhere behind the text,
then we have to ask the question,
where that meaning resides, where is it?
Where would you find it?
Right.
So some folks, this is where the typical go-to's
of people responding to postmodernism
is to retreat to modernism and say,
Well, it's in the...
of the author. Yeah. It's the author's intent, right? It's what the author intended to say.
That's the real meaning. Which, okay, how do you get that? Yeah. Like, not only do you have to do
mind reading, you have to do time travel, mind reading. Right. Right. We have to try and get
into St. Paul's head. Right. Yeah. Very difficult to do. Right. And not easier than what's
interpreting what's on the page right?
It just doesn't ease it right?
And some...
cases, we don't even know who the part right who wrote first and second kings or third and fourth kingdoms.
You know, I never considered that question at all, actually, we don't know. Do we?
No, we don't. So whose brain are we even trying to get into?
Yeah, right. How would you determine the intent of an completely unknown author?
Yeah, or even, I mean, like to narrow it down a little bit,
you know, how do we get into the mind of whoever wrote the end of Deuteronomy?
You know what?
describing Moses's death and funeral.
Right.
Yeah.
And so some folks will try to escalate it a step,
because they'll say, well, look, scripture, sort of in a sense,
has two authors.
There's a human author.
But what's really important in scripture is what God
intends it to mean.
Right?
That's not easier.
Right.
Alright.
We have slightly better idea of what it's like to be St. Paul.
Then we do want it to be God.
Yeah, exactly.
Right.
So that's going to be tough.
So another answer, right, that you'll get is that, well, you look elsewhere in
scripture, right?
Scripture and turpored scripture scripture interprets itself.
Right.
You read the clear passages and you use those to interpret the unclear passages.
Right? Right. But this pretty well begs the question. Yeah, because first of all, yeah,
first of all, it's completely subjective, which texts are clear and which ones are unclear.
Right? Was that I think are clear might be very unclear to you. And what's interesting is,
what passages people think are clear tend to correspond to the tradition they're coming from.
tend to correspond to their own subjectivity.
So my Calvinist friends find Romans 3.
Romans 5 and Romans 9 through 11, incredibly clear.
Crystal clear.
Right.
It's totally obvious what they're saying.
People from other traditions, not so much.
Right.
And this is true.
Hey, to be fair, right.
Partakers of the divine nature in second Peter, right.
Ask any orthodox person.
That's what they're out of.
Crystal clear.
That's talking about theosis.
Right.
Now the
I can't go through the verses before and after it explained how theosis fits in there,
but they will tell you that that verse is about theosis, right? Totally clear.
And so what this shows us is that perceived clarity and lack of clarity is really based
in our own subjectivity, right? And so that makes that problematic. But beyond even that,
beyond even that. Even a clear passage I still have to read and interpret. I just...
think it's easy, but I still have to read it and interpret it. I have to discern the
meaning of that quote unquote clear passage. Right. In order to use it to interpret another
passage. Right. Because it's a very least, you know, books with words on the page don't
talk to you and correct you and make you do stuff like just still application that has
to happen. And that means interpretation. Like there's no way around it. Right. You
You haven't told me where the meaning of the clear passage lies.
Right, you're just claiming to me that it's obvious
Which is a dubious claim as we were just saying right?
Right and implies and implies if you don't agree
You're either a liar, you know, you're like you're your suspect or you yeah, you're doing something fishy
Yeah, right or you're just too dumb trying to buddy the waters to get it or uninformed, you know
It's that that trifecta of you know the the person who disagrees you do is either evil
on and
intelligent or uninformed. Yeah. Yeah. So that's usually an answer you get more from our
Protestant friends. Right. When you get more from Orthodox folks is some idea that usually
won't use this Latin term because Latin is bad if you're Orthodox. But some idea of
the consensus potterum, right, that the consensus of the fathers, right? The fathers, that's
where you get the meaning. The fathers have the correct meaning of each biblical passage.
you go, that's how Orthodox people read the Bible, right?
They'll tell you that.
Right.
So here's the problems with that.
Number one, the way most people do that is they go and grab
their ancient Christian commentary on scripture,
which by the way was translated by somebody
and compiled by somebody.
And published by...
Interversity Press, right?
Yeah, and neither of those people are Orthodox
for our right, friends.
Unless you're reading the Arabic language version, exception.
But anyway, is there an Arabic version of that?
There is.
And the general editor in charge of the translations is a priest in our own archdiocese.
Not me, right?
Obviously.
No, no.
Arabic, right?
You don't know.
You don't do Arabic.
How about that?
Not so much.
A little bit.
A bit, you know, I didn't widen.
You know what I mean?
Um, but...
So, but you so people will go and then look there, look up the verse.
Okay, well, here's here's eight comments from early Christian writers and you weed out
the two or three who are heretics and then you say, well, either they're all kind of saying
the same thing.
So I guess that's what the verse absolutely means.
And then you stop there.
Yeah.
they're saying different things.
And now you got a problem, right? So you can either say, well, like apparently there is no clear,
the fathers all disagree. So you don't have to worry about them or you get this weird thing.
This weird post-modern thing that is unfortunately incredibly common in Orthodox circles,
where they will say, well, okay, so I see that the fathers have one of these
two opinions on what V1 meaning is of this passage. And therefore, these are the options
I have.
Yeah, I can pick one.
I get to pick one of those two.
It's quote in the tradition or something like that.
I'm allowed to believe either A or B, right? Here's why this is completely postmodern in
its approach, right? Because here are the things that assumes. It assumes that either there
is no actual meaning of that text.
Number one, or two, it's completely inaccessible, right? This is exactly what we were just saying about postmodernism.
The meaning is there behind the text, but in this case, because the father's disagree, we can't know what it is.
We just have these two perspectives. Just pick a father that you like better.
Right. We have these two perspectives. And then we have this idea of being allowed to be added.
that allowed there means what?
It means that the church's exercise
comes some kind of force or power.
power. The ghost of Michelle Foucault has entered the room. Right? And is this power? And so has
compelled us to choose one of these two options. But I am allowed to choose either of the two. And if
someone comes along and tells me that one of those two is wrong, I say, how dare you. You are saying
that this church father was a heretic or was wrong or whatever, right? This is pure...
pure postmodernism. Yeah, and then on people. On top of that, then also is, and by the way,
I'm interpreting that church father correctly. Right. But we'll get to that a little bit more
as we go. Right. Right. Yeah. Right. So, yeah. So we have this problematic now. Right. If you're
going to take that modernist approach, that there is a meaning back there, it's very difficult to
to discern even where that means.
would lie, right? And it's very easy to just lapse from modernism and depose modernism when you get
frustrated trying to figure out what that meaning is, right? Just decide this is impossible, right?
Right. Throw your hands up. Yeah. So another version of this, a more nuanced version of this,
this, shall we say. Right? And this is very common is that people will suggest that we should
basically...
read the fathers and the scriptures backwards. Yeah, later stuff interprets the earlier stuff.
Right. So you read the fathers, use the fathers to interpret the New Testament, use the New Testament to interpret the Old Testament.
Right. And so that sounds reasonable at first. Sure. Right. A lot of people hear that just accept it. Right. Many of our listeners probably just have accepted that in the past. Right.
Now, let me problematize that a little bit, right?
Because what is this presuppose?
Well, this presuppose is, if we go,
and we're going to go, fathers, New Testament, Old Testament,
that each one of those is clearer than the next, right?
So the fathers, I could read the fathers
and what the fathers are saying about Scripture,
how their interpretive Scripture is totally clear.
So that I can use that to understand the more difficult passages in the New Testament,
so that I can use those to understand the even more difficult passages in the Old Testament.
Right.
And well, I would submit, first of all, this is on the face not true.
Right? You are not going to convince me that it is easier to understand any of St. Maximus, the Confessor's ambiguous,
than it is to understand.
the parable of the prodigal son.
Right.
Exactly.
You're
it's
right.
I mean, just on its face.
Right.
I'm not saying, understand every nuance of the parable of the prodigal son.
Say Maximus could help us with that.
But the gist.
Right.
Christ parables.
He told to peasant farmers, illiterate peasant farmers and he communicated to them.
Right.
The means of salvation.
So this is not...
right and there are plenty of passages of the Old Testament, you know, the 10 commandments
are pretty clear, right? We don't need a ton of, right, like nuance to crack that code,
right? So that's a problem. There's also the problem that everything requires interpretation.
You have to interpret the fathers too. Right, right, right. The fathers, I don't know of
any fathers.
this way, who write in very simple straightforward, easy to understand Greek that doesn't require
you to have any knowledge of the Bible or philosophy going into it.
Right.
Even like Chrysostom, who is one of the most, I don't know, at least, and I mean, I'm reading
a meaningless translation.
Often a lot of what you read in translation is some of the most accessible stuff, but he's
making all kinds of references, especially to the Bible.
And to other like he's not giving you, you know, you don't come to Christophe,
I'm Tabir Rasa, you come, you know, he's making reference to things that you should know.
He assumes, you know, he assumes his listeners know some of what he's talking about.
Right.
You know, so if you're, if you're coming to the New Testament only through the fathers
and to the Old Testament only through the New Testament and the fathers, right?
You're not gonna have a good...
time, right? Because you're you're going to have a lot of trouble understanding the fathers.
If you don't know anything about the old New Testaments. Yeah, right. Exactly. Yeah. And
likewise, you have to interpret the New Testament, right? And the New Testament kind of assumes
you've read the Old Testament, right? Like that's constantly quoting it, right? And applying
it right? So it assumes you've read it. So we're starting to get to the
into the tunnel here. The light is starting to get bigger. Now I know sometimes the shifting
light at the end of your tunnel is just a freight train coming your way. But not in this case.
Right. In this case it is hope. Yes. So what we're suggesting and what we've been doing in this
show ever since it started is the opposite of this it's reading forward. It's reading the old
Old Testament.
coming to understand the Old Testament and what's going on there, right? Bringing that into the
New Testament to see how the New Testament reshapes, fulfills, transforms, transfigures the Old Testament,
and then moving into the fathers to see how they understand and apply both.
Right.
Right, I mean, and if you look, like, you know, if you look, for instance, at the liturgical
text, which I would, I consider to be...
in some sense a subset of the fathers.
Like, the liturgical texts are patristic writings.
Yes.
Right.
Some of them quite literally like St. John of Damascus.
Yes.
Right.
Exactly.
We know.
Yeah, particular fathers wrote them.
If you don't have a pretty thorough knowledge of the Bible, you're not going to get a lot of
what's in there.
I mean, really, it's so allusive.
You know, and so like the idea, and I mean, you sometimes get this, like there's this
This little subset.
while treating the divine services
as being sort of infallible guides
that always interpret the scripture correctly.
And I mean, there's something to that of course, as we've said,
but again, they assume that you know
that you're already familiar with the scriptures, right?
So it becomes a kind of a feedback loop.
You know, it doesn't quite work as being a key to the Bible.
In many ways, as you said, it kind of goes the other direction
to understand the litter
you really need to know the Bible. Right, right. Yeah. And so now the time has come
that I'm going to say something nice about George William Frederick Hagle. Here it goes. Yes.
Yeah. This is not the only night. It's what a very relatively few things, nice things I have to say
about him. Another one that springs to mind, just because it's funny.
before we get into the actual one is that at one point,
Hagle did this extended debunk of frenology,
which was considered a science in the early 19th century.
What do you want?
Look that up everybody what frenology is at pH, R, E, N.
Brodo, you need to know to get his joke, right?
So, okay, okay.
Ferdology was measuring people's heads,
and shapes of people's heads to determine their character.
And it was used for a lot of horrible...
racist pseudoscience. Yeah. Yeah. In the 19th century. So,
Heygill has this extended debunk. And toward the end of it,
he says that if someone comes to you and starts talking about
frenology, the correct response is to crack their skull.
So I do like that about. He was, he was an early, I mean, he
would totally if he was alive today have a YouTube video like.
for anology destroyed.
You know, like,
but so that's not the
destroyed.
That's not the nice thing I was
going to say about it.
Oh, there's two nice things
that you need to say about it.
Yes.
I didn't want people to think
what I'm about to say,
the more important thing is
the only thing.
And we should also mention
everybody that it's not the
same thing as nephrology,
which is, you know, your
local kidney doctors and
the frologist or
phleb bottomy, which is the
guy who takes blood out of
So just put it up.
That's a full bonus. Yes, yes. Okay.
But so here is the nice thing about Hagle relevant to this.
So Hagle is usually credited with being the one who
introduced the concept of history to philosophy.
In that, in that, right?
So people talked about ideas or concepts before Hagle in philosophy.
They thought of philosophers as sort of like talking
heads like floating
talking heads, right? So like Plato says this, Aristotle says this, yeah, right? Pure concepts,
right? And interacting with them and some of them saw development, right? Obviously this later
guy builds on this earlier guy, right? You know, Plato's a student of Socrates, Aristotle's a student
of Plato, right? Etc. Right? But so then when it's when you have this concept of building, right?
or if you're, for example, a west...
Christian, you'd say Thomas Aquinas built on Aristotle, right? Then what you
want, if somebody's building on someone else's, you want the latter part, right?
So Thomas Aquinas took all the good parts of Aristotle, so just take him, you
don't have to worry about Aristotle anymore, right? Yeah. One of one of two
approaches, right? But so when Hagle talks about concepts, he talks about them
growing organically through time. Right?
So it's like you have a stem and then it buds and then the flower opens
Right and when that happens you don't like cut off the stem in the bud and just keep the petals
Because that's the important part that was at the end of the chain
right
or to give another example that Hagle himself uses
If you want to claim to understand an oak tree you also have to understand an acorn
Right and a sapling
Right, you have to-
understand the the organism all the way through right not just the end result.
Right. Yeah, it's not the end result is not just the latest greatest version and so we don't need.
You know, it's not like getting a new cell phone.
Where you know, it's better than all the previous cell phones that you don't need now.
Right. And so I think this bit from Hegel is helpful as an analogy.
That's why I'm bringing it up. Yeah. Right. Yeah. We're not Hagealians.
aliens. We're not endorsing
Oh, that's going to be all over Reddit tomorrow.
Sure.
Your spirit is a Gaelian.
But that this is helpful for thinking about scripture.
Right.
In that you see truth, which is Christ ultimately, introduced in the Old Testament and then
it grows and it comes to flower in the New Testament.
Right.
of Jesus Christ in the full revelation of Jesus Christ in the
New Testament. Exactly. Right. And when that happens, you don't throw the Old Testament
away. No. Right.
They certainly didn't because in order to really understand the full revelation of Christ in
the New Testament, you have to also understand the Acorn. Right. You have to understand the
beginning and the growth and the development up to the fulfillment and the flowering. Right.
And this kind of approach is why we're always starting in the new...
era on this show. There you go, right, or the beginning of Genesis, right? And tracing these things
through. Because to understand how they come to flower and be fulfilled in Christ, you have to
follow that growth. You have to follow that gradual unfolding, right? That happens through the
scripture. So on a more practical, now we're going to get more practical, and we're going to get
really practical in the third half.
right? But here's we're coming toward the end of half two. So we talked about, we're coming back to
where we started here in act two, which where does that meaning lie? Right? So we're not going with
the modernist presupposition. We don't think each text, each verse, each passage has this one single
meaning that's off somewhere and locatable. Right? But then how do you go about beginning to interpret
these texts. If we're going to go through the old test of it, the new test of it and watch
these things grow and unfurl, right?
Right. And we're definitely not, we're definitely not saying because we don't think that there's
a single objective meaning for every single text that there's no, therefore no meaning
or that any meaning goes. Like that's definitely not what we're saying. And I think that's, there's
no single. Yeah. Right. And I think that's, that's the big fear is like, okay, well, look
if you sort of lose that sense of scientific,
scientificity,
you know, of of of this then then what are you left with, right? Like just all relativism.
But if you're not a modernist, you must be a postmodernist.
Right. And and you know what everybody? Those are not the only options.
Yes. Those are not the thankfully. Yeah. Right. Right.
Uh, right. Exactly. So unless you're writing a dissertation at certain universities,
because they are the only options. But no, so, so, don't go. What's the beginning of it?
approach, right? A beginning of an approach is rather than trying to reconstruct the mind
from which the text emanates, we try to reconstruct the ear. The people who heard these texts first.
We're not going for any specific person here. Right. In their individuality and their subjectivity.
We're going for a time, a place, a people group.
right that we can know relative amounts about. How would they have heard this text? Right?
This is a starting point, not an ending point, right, but this is a starting point. Right.
So what are some examples of this? So test case for this. Giants and demons. Right.
Something we talk about a fair amount. Our ratings just went up for this episode.
because you just mentioned Giants. Everyone got very excited.
So, and this is some interactions we've gotten about when we talk about giants, right?
We get essentially requests that we have to prove that Nephilim are giants.
We have to prove exactly what being a giant man.
Can you prove that, right?
And that's taking this modernist approach, right?
We love you.
You're saying, yes, but that's what's going on.
We love you, but you need to set yourself free from the chains of modernism.
that unshackled. Because what that question presupposes is there's this one
meaning behind the text, you need to prove to me that this meaning you're
proposing is the one meaning, right? You're making this claim, right? And then
are they tall people? Are they like genetic hybrids of angel and human? Or
that, right? So
We're approaching it more from the perspective of, okay, when the first readers of, or early readers at least,
of Genesis 6, 1 through 4, when they heard that about the sons of God and the daughters of men.
And they heard about the Nephilim, the men of her now.
What connections would they have reasonably made?
Yeah.
And we know thanks to second-tabled Jewish literature, ancient Eastern literature, we know
the other stories they had heard. We know how they would have seen these references connecting
to each other. These are the connections they would have made. We're not arguing about this
hypothetical one single meaning behind it. We're saying, no, this is how people read it.
Right, and going from Giants to Demons, right, this is why that book, I want to say Archie Leech again.
He's haunting me.
Very grand.
And I'm blanking on it too.
The origin of evil spirits.
Right.
Right. What he does is he goes to the first century.
Who did first century people living in Judea based on their writings,
based on the text, the stories that were going around.
they think these demons that were possessing people came from.
From Archie right. Archie right. No, yeah, where did they think it was? Yeah, yeah, we think these demons came from
Yeah, yeah, the people who first read the Gospels that read these accounts of Christ's Catholic out demons
And if you come to tour minister for the time, what did they think that meant? How would they have read that?
Which is a separate question from were they wrong about this were they right about because like
If they're wrong about it, then you know then
and how am I supposed to be right about it?
Like, what do I have that they...
didn't. Well, even that question, were they right? Right. What does that mean? Again, that's
treating the Bible as if you're saying that this exorcism story in the gospel claim is making a claim,
right? It's not making a claim. Right. Exactly. It's telling a story. Yeah. And the context in which
that story was heard. Yeah. And I think that this issue underlines how heart this is. I mean, as
modern people.
This is simply the way that we think.
Right?
So we have to, part of our project on this podcast is to try to at least give us a framework
that we can enter into for a while, to try to begin to think differently, not to try
to make everything into an empirical quest.
Because some things, if you embark on that, if you embark on a empirical quest to understand
what's in the scripture.
going to actually miss the way that people received it when it was first given.
Because they weren't on that quest. Right. Right. There was no quest for the
historical Jesus before the 18th century. Yeah. Just wasn't it wasn't it didn't
happen. Um, so, um, another test case, another example, right? I hate to bash our
Calvinist friends. Do you? For the sake of argument I do.
But Romans nine, right? Romans nine.
When St. Paul brings up Jacob and Esau, he's talking about Jacob and Esau to people who
are incredibly familiar with the story of Jacob and Esau that's contained in Genesis.
Yeah.
He was not bringing up two hypothetical people, one of them good and one of them evil.
Right.
them loved by God and one of them hated by God.
God, one of them elected, one of them reprobate. He's not bringing up to random people, right?
The people who first heard him make that argument, knew that story. So they knew, for example,
that Jacob and Esau reconciled at the end of that story. They knew they had read Deuteronomy
two and knew that at that point, the Edamites were still worshiping Yahweh, the God of Israel.
And the itemites are eSaus people, right away everybody.
and they had read on to Obadaya and seen that that changed later and that's when they were judged.
And so when they hear St. Paul talking, right, we don't have to try to get inside St. Paul's head
and see what it's trying to do. We can see how anyone familiar with that story would understand what he's saying.
And you can go listen to a certain episode of Whole Council of God on that if you want to.
it's not Calvin's approach.
Right. If you take the actual story into account, uh, right. Right.
He's he's importing that whole history in that, uh, that old sense, that whole history
from the Old Testament into his conversation. Right. Yeah. And so reading, reading what he says is
contrary to that history, then, therefore does not make sense. Right. Yeah. Right. And the response,
when I point that out of well, you have to use the new testament to interpret the Old Testament.
but so St Paul is saying that...
is what Genesis means.
Again, it's kind of a quasi postmodern thing, right?
Like, I've got to go back and read Genesis
against the grain now to try and make it mean
what you say St. Paul means.
Yeah.
Yeah, why is St. Paul negating Genesis?
Yeah. Why would he do that?
Like if he's gonna do that, he needs to explain why he's doing that.
And he doesn't say he's doing that.
Yeah. He doesn't say he's doing it.
And say he's doing it on apostolic authority
This also works.
cop out because you're essentially arguing that St. Paul was given authority by the Holy
Spirit to interpret the Bible badly, which doesn't make a lot of sense.
No.
So, third test case, because we've got to do things in three where orthodox.
Yeah.
It's three or forty.
So, forty.
A key to twelve.
Yeah.
Once in a while, a hundred.
A third test case, which is a place where people have wasted a ton of time.
of time, frankly. And this is comparing Isaiah 7, verse 14 and Matthew 1, verse 23. Behold,
a young woman or a version will bear a child and they'll cause name of manual.
Right. Right. So what causes the problem here,
right is that the word in the Hebrew Alma just means a young woman and
a virgin per se, parthenos by the first century that St. Matthew uses, the first century
mostly meant a virgin.
Yeah, but it also meant a young woman.
A young woman.
At the time, the Greek translation of the Old Testament was made, it was more a young
woman also.
But anyway, so people get into this whole thing of Oceania doesn't say virgin.
So they treat, they're doing this thing we talked about.
saying, Saint Matthew claims.
that Isaiah predicted a virgin birth.
And so if we can prove that that's not what Isaiah was claiming,
then Saint Matthew's claim is false.
So the Bible's false Christianity goes away, right?
Check that out.
Right.
But so if we instead of reading this backward,
read this forward, right, then when we read Isaiah 7,
we'll read the whole chapter maybe,
and see that this is in the middle of the Ciro E freo might war.
which was very poorly named because it was not a war between the Syrians and the
Ephraimites. It was a war in which the Syrians and the Ephraimites, the northern
Kingdom of Israel, attacked Judah. But the attack Judah, Judah was at
dire straits. They were losing Isaiah comes and makes this prophecy and says this
young woman standing here is going to have a baby and before that baby is old
enough to know right from wrong.
Right? For his old enough to know good or evil
You'll be delivered from the combined army of the the Syrians and the the Israelites, right?
And that happened it happened it Isaiah and happened to the Old Testament
Right, right that prophecy he made came true
Okay, right he wasn't talking at that time about a virgin birth
He wasn't talking about anything happening in the first century AD and
St Matthew isn't claiming he was
Hmm right because that's not how this works right the truth comes it flowers right
Full fill this idea of fulfillment being filled full to overflow overflowing so what St. Matthew is doing is saying hey
You guys who have already Isaiah you've all heard Isaiah read in the synagogues every day of your life
Well, they're not every day every Saturday of your life
That's every Sabbath
You've heard this story a hundred times right and you remember how
The birth of that child signaled that the delivery of God's people was near.
Well, guess what?
Right.
Guess what?
Even Murth of Christ, that he's describing in Matthew 1, the birth of Christ in this much
fuller, richer, deeper, eternal sense means that God is now going to shortly deliver his
people.
Yeah.
And I think one of the things that's really important to underline in the midst of this,
like you just said, they would have heard this for instance every Saturday, their lives
in the synagogue.
I think we should underline that because the way that a lot of modern people approach
biblical interpretation is largely looking at a book that maybe they don't know the nooks
and crannies of and haven't heard the same stories a hundred times before.
Right.
I mean, some people certainly that know the Bible very, very well, but
When even people that do know it really well,
we receive it in the midst of a culture full of all kinds
of other stories, constantly.
Like this is the massive information age, right?
Whereas in first century Holy Land,
yes, there were other stories going on
in their culture other than what's in the Bible,
but nowhere near like what we have,
and they were richly participating in these stories
over and over.
over and over again. So they all grew up hearing them. They all, they, they, the, the, the
general culture knew the Old Testament way better than most Christians today do. Because
they were just in it all the time, right? And so then when the New Testament makes illusions
or references or quotes from the Old Testament, it's, it's, it's, it's importing it. It's
a stuff much more powerfully than it is even for us. Like we have to look at little marginal
notes like, oh, is that a reference to some...
thing in Isaiah? You know, I mean, this is obvious of our famous example, but you know, they
would not have needed these cross-reference Bibles to the extent that we do now, because
this was just simply, these are their societal stories. This is the history of this people.
You know, it's embedded in a way that I think it's hard for us to really, really get. I
mean, I think people who belong to the liturgical churches who are really dedicated to being
and services a lot begin to get this.
Like I've seen it with my
kids that they know so many biblical stories that I never, you know, to my shame, that I didn't
read them all to them, but they know them why because they're in church, because they're hearing
them, they're richly participating in them. Yeah, and even if you absolutely hate my approach,
at least it saves me a lot of these unending arguments. Yeah, yeah, exactly. All right, well, that's it.
We're gonna go ahead and take a break and we'll head on into our third
half will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Big in Heaven.
A collection of short stories available now on the Ancient Faith Bookstore.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking, sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant Orthodox parish are guaranteed to shake your
assumptions and make you see your life and face in a new way. They are not for the faint of heart,
but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask, cross-gover for help.
Cleaning, polishing.
carrying in or out, any work in the church the woman was astalled, a talladeesh you could
count on. No one knew her suffering. They never bothered to look into her eyes. It surprised
me that most of the church folks at St. Alexander the Rolling Dirt Parish didn't even know her
name. It wasn't anything they thought about.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enginefei.com. Again, that
This door...
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits here the week before Holy Week.
if you're listening to us live.
So we're right right on the cusp of hearing a big massive pile of scripture in church
Which is always just such an amazing amazing experience. So okay, so we've gone you know
To the end of the tunnel. We've seen some light done some of you test cases
How do we kind of take this forward like how do we?
integrate this right into the way that we think and to the way that we interpret
the Bible the way that we read the
Bible into the way that we think about how the Orthodox Church does those things, right?
So how do we interpret it?
Oh, did I lose your father, Stephen?
I think we might have lost him.
Did I lose me?
All right folks, we seem to be having a little bit of technical difficulty here.
It's been a long time since we had technical difficulties.
Nope.
All right.
Um.
Okay, well, we're going to go ahead and while we try to get Father Stephen back on the
line, we're going to go ahead and take a caller who is calling, I believe, from Canada,
or at least his phone number says he's in Canada.
So I'm not sure how to pronounce your name.
You're going to have to tell me, are you there?
Caller?
Yeah, this is Rado from the Canada.
Rado, okay, welcome.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
How are you this evening?
trying to get Father Steven back so I can't guarantee.
that I would necessarily say whatever he would say, but what's on your mind?
I think you're taking my call, Father.
Yeah, I was just wondering what you kind of started touching on the end of the last half, which is
we talked a lot about how the text should be interpreted and used that word a lot, but I'm also
thinking about how people would have interacted with all this 12th century of Romanian peasants,
You know, nobody can read.
or very, very few, they see the icons painted out of wall
in a country church.
They may be most of the Texas not a language,
they can understand the literature,
you might not be in a language, they understand.
Yeah.
It's all either oral tradition
or you see a bunch of icons on the wall,
the spress goes on the outside of the monastery church,
they see once a year on pilgrimage,
that sort of thing and how all of this discussion
would have been relevant and real for them
in that kind of non-textual world.
Yeah.
So, I mean, right, I mean most people are not listeners to Lord of Spirits.
You know, most people are not doing biblical scholarship.
Most people are not diving into these questions in the way that we're talking about them, right?
So there's, you know, even like within the scenario you're talking about, I mean, it's
still even now most people are simply hearing the descriptions in church, right?
That's how they're getting it, right?
So yeah, I mean, I think that what we're talking, I mean, we're analyzing this from a very
kind of intellectual point of view on a certain level, but the way that most people,
the way that most people are actually experiencing church, right, actually does,
does produce this for them, right?
Like, like, friends, as I think about my own kids,
they're growing up in church,
they're hearing the stories of the scripture, right?
And so they receive all of this together
as one narrative experience, right?
For them, unless I tell them, look,
the Old Testament and New Testament
are not one integrated piece,
they have no reason to believe that it's not, right?
So what's happened is that there's a lot of weeds
of grown-up within culture that have...
made it hard for people to simply have that experience of simply growing up with scriptures and growing,
you know, growing up with all of these things that are connected together. Right? I mean, we've
said a bunch of times, you don't have to have read the book of Enoch in order to receive the
scriptures in the church for your salvation. Right? You don't have to have done that.
But if you are faithful within the church
I'm not saying you have to have grown up with it, but if you are faithful and are willing as much as possible to
to be taught by what you're experiencing, then you will begin to get it.
A lot of what we're trying to do is try to clear away the weeds of modern culture that are simply there and that we can't you know
We we can't help but have to deal with it, right?
Does that make some sense?
Yeah, yeah, it doesn't. It's also quite
because I have young kids so that's good.
All right, I mean, it's been fascinating to me
to watch my kids, like my oldest is 15 and my youngest is five.
And then I have a 12 year old and an almost 10 year old.
It's been fascinating to me to watch them
the way that they understand the scripture,
the way that they understand the story that the church is telling,
is actually very different from, in many ways,
the way that I do...
Or in some cases I've had to work really hard to get to where they are just growing up with it naturally.
Right? And you know, if they don't ever want to be biblical scholars or even just sort of fans of biblical scholarship, which is kind of what I sort of am,
that's okay. You know, like they don't have to be, they can still receive this for their salvation.
They can even still have this integrated view.
Like one of the things that I've sort of observed is that
A lot of Christians these days are functionally Marcianists, right?
You know, Marcian, that early church heretic who basically said the Old Testament, you should
throw it out because that's an evil God who created the world and that's not the father
of our Lord Jesus Christ.
A lot of Christians are functionally Marcianists.
Like, I've even heard people within the Orthodox church say to me, I'm going to say, I'll
make a reference to the Old Testament and they'll say, oh, well, you know, we don't need
that anymore.
We have the New Testament.
And that's exactly what we're talking about.
It's like, yeah.
I mean, that's a really terrible version of it, even.
The idea that the Old Testament doesn't even matter anymore.
So does that make sense?
Yeah, yeah, thank you, Father.
Can I have just a tiny, tiny little follow-up?
Sure, absolutely.
Which is more of a tiny suggestion.
I'd like to throw in Golden Jubilee Hall Senior Center
and Sussex New Brunswick as a location for the first
Bye.
inaugural Lord of Spirits of Paloosa.
Oh, we'll get you all.
Well, all right.
We will take that under their advisement.
So thank you very much, Rodu.
Okay.
All right.
So I think a long time co-host first time caller.
Hey, there you are.
So yeah.
Well, welcome back.
Yes. So as you can hear, everybody,
we've got fathers even on the phone.
But but but there you are.
Everybody.
Yeah.
Everything's going badly.
Okay.
So anyway, well, not ideal, but we can understand you.
So all right.
Well, yeah, yeah, we actually, okay.
So we have one more caller and why don't we talk to Matt?
So Matt, what's on your mind?
Are you guys there?
Yes.
I was wondering how to interpret scripture
through the news, the noretically.
I think I'll pass.
I forget what does it father was I think I can never pronounce his name right
Markevi is or whatever the name was how he explains eco one as a
surrender soul and I feel like that might be like a no way of attempting
scripture but yeah like like that's an example of honest things scripture through
the news. Father Steven you want to start off on that one? Well that's I mean
And that's kind of what we're going to be talking about in this.
So, there you go. That's a good thing that each of you are tracking with it.
Yeah, and so, yeah, we're about to go back to the fathers and sort of talk about what they're doing and how they're doing it.
Right? And what that idea of the phronema, the way of the
the neuatic way of reading the scriptures of the fathers do.
what that is if it isn't sort of taking a straw poll of
patricity quotes.
I said, and then judging from that.
So I guess mainly my unsatisfactory answer is stay tuned here.
Okay.
All right.
So hang on and just keep going with us.
So thank you very much for calling.
Okay.
So father, since before we got so rudely interrupted by whatever it
happened to your equipment there.
Yeah, well, great that nation. Yeah. Oh boy. Yeah. Yeah. So, yeah. So we talked about, you know,
at the end of half two, we talked about sort of moving from the Old Testament into the New Testament,
but we sort of just mentioned didn't forget about the fathers. You aren't just casting them aside,
I did it in the quag-
question is, if the truth comes to flower in the revelation of Christ in the New Testament,
then what are the fathers do?
And again, we have to make a distinction between the idea of interpretation and the idea of
application.
These are two different things.
So interpretation more describes what we've been talking about in a more negative sense.
idea that the fathers are looking at the text of scripture and trying to
ascertain this one true meaning, right, that lies behind it. And that when they
therefore say different things, that means they disagree about what that one
meaning is. Right. Right. Whereas we're going to suggest application is
something different and a good way.
way, a good orthodox way of thinking about that distinction is the theological distinction
we make between essence and energy.
We make that distinction in terms of God as we've talked about on the show.
We make that distinction about everybody.
Sure.
Right.
It's also worth thinking about in terms of the scriptures and their interpretation.
So when we talk about the distinction between God's essence and his energies, what we're saying is that
God is not like an essence
He's not a being even a supreme being that we comprehend with our intellect
Right that we go and perform an intellectual process and arrive at exactly who God is
But rather, we encounter God in action.
Right.
The right energies are God, but they're God in action.
We encounter God loving, we encounter God transfiguring, we encounter God saving, we encounter
God justifying, setting things right.
And so we should think about meaning in terms of the scriptures in much the same way.
Right.
And this is what we're suggesting the fathers do.
the fathers are not.
not peering into the Bible and trying to use an intellectual process to arrive at the essence
of this or that verse or this or that passage, this meaning that underlies it, right, that
stands behind it, to intellectually comprehend what it is, but that through the scriptures
God has encountered an action because God is acting through the scriptures.
And so, as God is working through the scriptures, in...
applying those scriptures, right, whether they're doing it sort of in a direct way as when St.
John Krasostom is preaching a homily after the reading of the scripture that he's taking them and
and applying them or a little more subtly as, you know, St. Gregory the Thayologian when he
writes a treatise on a current Trinitarian debate, right, and reference this scripture,
they are participating sort of instrumentally as an instrument.
of God through which the work that God is doing in Scripture is applied, right, to the people who are
under their spiritual authority. Yeah, in their particular time and place. And if we think about it
that way, that has a whole bunch of consequences, right, over again, the kind of interpretation model.
It means that scripture, we need to think of scripture more as a mystery.
in the sense that that word is used in the Orthodox Church, right?
To talk about things in the West are called sacraments.
Yes, right.
Sort of a material thing that the reading of Scripture is a material thing, an audible thing,
through which God works, through which the divine energies are made.
Present God Himself becomes present in a transformative way for people.
And if we accept that this is the way the
reading of scripture primarily works,
then that means that like all mysteries,
like all sacraments,
the proper home of them is within the liturgical life
of the church.
Right, there's sort of a niche and proper home.
So that also then has its own consequences, right?
And we're not really used to thinking this way,
because again we're in
the modern or postmodern contemporary world.
And we've been by our culture, if not,
the church we attended, we've been encouraged
to see sort of our own personal sitting down
and reading the Bible as being the primary venue
of the Bible.
Yeah, right.
Pictures work.
That Bible study equals me alone,
doing
this thing with this book. Right. Right. And we wouldn't say that about any other mystery
slash sacrament. Right. Like I know there are people who do this, but hopefully most of our
listeners would understand why the whole communion for one thing is kind of out. Right. Yeah.
Although it didn't happen on the moon.
Yeah.
So literally way out there.
You've done things, but...
Yes.
Or someone going and baptizing themselves,
other than Robert Duval and the Apostle.
Yes.
Excellent.
So, right.
But the same is true in Scripture.
That Scripture because it's natural home,
is that the liturgical life of the church,
that means it's primary mode of reading
is being read.
publicly, being read aloud. And the Hebrew word for read is even the verb that means to
call out. So it's out loud.
So it's sitting thing. Yeah.
Yeah. And I think that in most of most of history, at least, you know, the more the European
history that I'm aware of, reading out loud is the way that you read until I don't know,
Like, pretty late.
You know, like, it's pretty late that...
that the texts were not read silently hardly ever.
Yeah, yeah. And and St. Augustine mentions knowing a crazy person.
And the reason everybody thought he was crazy was that he read to himself.
Yeah, without reading words coming in. He's sound coming out.
Yeah, because everyone else, even if they were sitting in their house by themselves,
reading something they read it out loud.
Yeah.
I was a complete weirdo.
But that gives you an idea of
right
understanding that collective
initial
context and
By it being in the context of a liturgical life of the church that means that whatever portion of scripture is read is also set in a larger
ritual and narrative context
So a good example of this
will be for folks a week from today when we read the 12 passion
gospels. We not only read the whole gospel accounts of Christ's passion and
all four gospels, right? But we do that in the context of a liturgical service
in which we also enact what's going on in those stories and so that those there
are brought into a participation in those events as we've talked about before.
for those events are made.
present, they're made now so that the people can participate. And the reading of scripture
is a part of that, a part of that whole, right? These aren't sort of two separate things.
Like, oh, we do this kind of reenactment. And then we also read the story, right? Those are
together and together for a reason, right? Right. That is sort of the proper function. And even in just
your typical divine liturgy on a Sunday morning.
the divine liturgy itself is structured around the life and death and resurrection of Christ.
And so the portions of Scripture read during it are set in that context as they're read publicly for participation.
And so preaching that takes place, which, and this is a lot of the writing of the fathers, right, is some form of preaching and applying,
whether it's literally a transcribed
or whether it's up.
essentially a written sermon. It's
it's it's aimed at it would be a written
sermon because it's aimed at some particular
situations a particular audience at some
particular place and time. Right, whether it's
whether it's spoken aloud or whether it's
written and then someone went and read it
aloud because remember the recipients of
the writings were reading them aloud
right now. Not silently.
is always a form of application.
So it would correspond, if we're thinking about
the reading of scripture as a mystery or a sacrament,
it would correspond to, for example,
actually giving the people communion.
Or pushing the kids head under the water three times.
right? Right? Right? The actual direct application of
and participation by the preacher instrumentally
in the work of God that's taking place
through the scriptures.
Right, and I think one of the important things
to underline in that context is
like whether you're reading a patristic writing
that's particularly a homily,
or you're simply listening to a homily written
in your own time, delivered in your own time,
is that the context in which it's given
is an important...
an element and understanding even the homily, right? You know, that the way, I remember, for instance,
when I was in seminary, I mean, like there's cultural pieces to this too. I remember when I was in
seminary that someone gave a sermon, which was very exercised, you know, a lot of, a lot of
very strong emotional expressions and so forth. And I thought to myself, oh, this is kind of similar
to some of the some of the Baptist preachers that I heard when I was younger, but we actually had a
a seminarian from Europe, from Northern Europe, who said, you know, if someone preached
like that in my home country, we would think of them like they were some kind of crazy
dictator. Right? So that did, you know, it was just received in a very different, and,
you know, in Northern Europe, they know something about crazy dictators. It was, you know,
it was just received, we'll say that again.
Yeah. They've seen a couple. Yeah, right. Right. And so let me so in his
case, he didn't have the cultural context that the rest of us did. And so he received it
very, very differently. Right. And then he took a completely other meaning from it that
it was different from the what the preacher intended and for what most of the hears heard.
So I mean, that context is really, really important. So even if a church father says X,
Y, Z, it's important to try to understand as much as possible the audience that he was
just saying that to the time, you know, what maybe...
historically happening in that place, you know, what are, you know, like all of that stuff matters,
all of that stuff matters because because it's precisely an action within a community. And so if you
pull a text outside of that community, then you shouldn't expect it to function exactly the same way
as when it was originally delivered. Right. Right. Because if the if the fathers are not trying to
communicate to us the secret essence of the scriptures that lies behind them.
Then what we're trying to do is not parent, right?
Some kind of claim that the fathers are making, right?
What we're trying to do is we're trying to do what they did.
Right.
We're trying to do the same thing.
And the only way to determine exactly what they're doing
is to understand what they actually did in their time and place
to that audience once, what the situation was
that they were addressing, what the debate
about that they were weighing in on. What the view is that they're criticizing or condemning
or warning against, right? If we don't understand those things, we won't understand what they're
doing. Right, because they're not pushing out pure encapsulated concepts into the ether.
You know, like these are not platonic forms of the dogmas or whatever, right? It's contextualized.
It's within it and that doesn't mean it's it's relativized
know, it's not postmodern. It's just seeing that this, this was not as you like to say sometimes,
you know, the scriptures are written for us but not to us. Right. You know, we're not the original
audience. Right. Right. And so a good example of this that's near and dear to my heart because
of the amount of my life that was spent on it is a lot of people go, who listen to the show at
at least that my dissertation was on first John Tuvers 2d
right? First John 2 verse 2 says that Christ died not only for our sins but for the whole world.
And if you go and look up the earliest commentary on that verse among the fathers,
what you find is that pretty much all the fathers from the 4th to the 8th century say that by
saying this St. John refutes the Donatists, which is a
weirdly anachronistic thing to say.
Yes, we're not aware of any donatists in the first century.
Right. Donatist himself lived in the fourth century.
So, right?
After whom it was named, he was not born yet.
Right?
So, it seems preposterous on the face to claim that, no,
those fathers are saying that the single accurate meaning of that verse.
referring to this specific North African heresy in the 4th century.
Right. 4th century. Right. This would be a preposterous argument. Right. It would make that
verse an any number of other passages of scripture completely irrelevant if you understood the fathers
that way. Right. And this is not a question of finding other later fathers who apply it to something
else right either right so what we have to do is
We have to look at the sort of larger context of St. John, and I'm not going to reiterate
my whole dissertation, thankfully, at this point in the evening.
But essentially what St. John is doing is he's talking about the shift that happens in
Christ from the way atonement worked in the old covenant, where it was for this one physical
Thank you, this one bit of land.
one structure in this one place among this one people. That's what was cleansed by these sacrifices.
And St. John is expanding that out to encompass the whole world.
And so what those fathers are saying is not that St. John had some kind of prophetic vision
that this heresy would arise in the four century. Right. But what the fathers are doing is
they're saying these donatists are making the same mistake that same
John was talking about.
They're trying to restrict salvation to just their group,
just their people, just in North Africa.
Right, they're trying to say where are the only ones
who have held onto the path of salvation.
Right, and St. John is saying no,
Christ made that available to the whole world.
And so therefore what St. John says
does refute the donatists among other people.
Right, so they're not misinterpreting it right, but what they're doing is they're applying it
Yeah, for their own time. I think I'm that
Applying it in their own time and place. This is what this means now for this issue we're facing right in the church
So
Going from the fathers to ourselves, right if we're gonna try to read the scriptures toward application in this way
Right try and make this move right sort of
God in action through the Scriptures.
How do we actually do that?
Right, so we've got some sort of quasi steps I guess I don't know if they're really steps
We've been better if we put it come up with steps
Five ways
That's a little biblical application
We could we could have made them like a literate, right?
We could have had like words that rhyme or words that all start with
We could be subtle and use S.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
First one starts with a
why so we could just go for the
bunch of a's. Yeah. Anyway,
the beginning there's a quote.
There's a quote from a church
father potentially.
They get to tribute it to a lot
of different people. I've used it.
They attributed it to various
people. So I'm keeping the
thing going.
I realized at one point.
Um.
So since the color brought up St. Macario,
so let's say it was St. Macario.
Um,
the quote is that the wise man applies everything in the scriptures to himself
and none of it to other people.
Right. Right.
And what he's talking about there is the idea that when we're doing this application,
one of the first principles that has to guide us is we're applying it to our
and potentially to if there is someone who we have spiritual careful. Right, like if you're a
pastor and you have a flock and it's your flock or you're a parent and you have children and
they're your children, then those are the people that you can apply it to, you know, in addition to
yourself. Right, right. But the core idea is if I walk away from the scriptures, saying, yeah,
those people over there rotten. I'm doing it wrong. Yeah. Right. I miss the boat. We don't find,
I put this challenge out a lot. Find me a place where the fathers talk about Christians going
to heaven and non-Christians going to hell. Well, that's the dividing line. Right. The reason
nobody's found one yet is the fathers don't spend a lot of time talking about people outside
church right because they're talking to their own flock
right and and they're often warning their own flocks about the potential of
going down right that that potentiality out there right that's what they're
concerned about not condemning the world outside of the church right so let
alone condemning their brother right so that's principle one you're looking at
at applying it to yourself first and foremost and then if there are others who
who are under your spiritual care.
for real, not who you've decided should be, right?
Then to them also, right?
But even in those cases, speaking to somebody
who preaches fairly frequently,
I've found it most effective that I approach it
as how do I need to apply it to myself?
What do I need to hear?
And then it's usually good assumption
that at least some of the people who I'm preaching to
Did you hear this?
same thing. There are enough like me and their humanity. Right. Also my my
needed applied in that way. Even though they don't know what it's like to be
Father Stephen D. Young. Yeah. Yeah. We're about. We're about.
I'm not claiming to be that. So when we're talking about applying,
Right, we're not talking about like thinking about virtues.
Right, applying is not reading and saying, yeah, that's true.
I need to exercise more self control.
That's not applying it.
Right.
That's amusing.
So remember we talked about this distinction
between essence and energy.
It's being counter-priced.
Right, as Christ is working in the world.
Right, when counter-God is working in the world.
And so sometimes
I think we lapse into thinking that an encounter with God will happen when we finally get some
peace and quiet and are able to meditate and say that Jesus prayer enough time for sequence.
And then we're going to have this encounter with God. But that's mostly not how it works.
Unless you're a monastic, right? If you're a monastic and you're called to go and you're one of
one of those tiny group of monastics is called to go into a hermit, right?
Then that may be how God...
relates to you, but for the rest of us, especially those of us who are out here in the world,
we're going to encounter him out here in the world. And that means to actually living,
living the scriptures, actually doing it. Yeah, which having the right opinions about it, but actually doing it.
Yeah, which explains why there's such an emphasis in the scriptures on what you do.
and even that.
the judgment where our eternal destiny is set is explicitly said over and over again
in the scriptures to be based on what you do. And even in Matthew chapter 25 with some
very specific actions in mind, right? That it's, yeah, Christ is not coming to judge
every man according to his opinions. He's coming to judge every man according to his works.
in Matthew 25 where, you know...
people are judged on whether they fed the hungry and called the naked and visited the sick and
in prison. Christ explicitly says, if you did that, you did it to me. If you didn't do it,
you didn't do it to me. In other words, the encounter with Christ is found in doing those works,
in doing the things that the commandments of God. I mean, I actually checked recently how many
times do you actually see this explicit pairing of if you love me keep my
commandments.
And I found 18 times just searching in the ESV, but there's the concept is even more ubiquitous like it's all over the place if you love Christ you keep his commandments.
You have to do that. There's just no way around it.
Right. And this this paradigm over and over again of those who hear the law versus those who do it. Right.
You're versus doing. Why do you call me Lord, Lord and not do what I say?
Alright.
Yeah. Yeah.
Exactly. Yeah, I mean, for instance, and and and one of the things I think that's that
also
underlines that is if we see
not just in the scripture where it says if you love me keep my commandments, but actually we do we do see
what the result of that is it says for instance the Lord says in Matthew 1917
if you would enter life.
keep the commandments. So, you know, if you keep the commandments, that means you're entering life.
That means you're entering into eternal life. You're doing it. You know, like we had a caller earlier asked about, you know, kind of is there any hope for interpreting the scripture correctly.
If you're not doing all this biblical study stuff, and of course I said yes, but also we should emphasize that even if someone understands intellectually,
Done.
everything we've just been talking about, but keeps the commandments of Christ actually
lives faithfully to him, then they're doing it. And it's not even, it's not like a lower
class version of Christianity. They're really doing Christianity. Like you can become a saint
without understanding the principles that we're talking about if you keep the commandments
of Christ because that's what sanctity actually is.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, and I mean the flip side then of course is if you're not keeping the commandments,
if you're not, then you're not living as a Christian.
And that means that your interpretation of the scriptures or of the fathers is
probably not worth a whole lot.
Maybe nothing.
Easily ignorable.
It's not that the things you're saying might be wrong, but the message you're also
delivering along with it is that, that this is the faith of demons.
Like I can be a...
jerk, I can be nasty and evil and not doing the things that Christ commanded and say things
that are true, but demons do that.
Yeah, I say James Floyd's out.
The demons know all that stuff for sure.
They don't just think it or believe it.
Right.
I mean, their dogma is the best.
They've got it really down.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Well, so to wrap up this evening,
conversation about methodology,
that's what this really was.
I think, now we've got enough episodes
that it's hard to tell people,
just simply listen to all of them.
Although I still think that that's the ideal.
But I will say though,
even if someone doesn't listen to all of them,
I think this is gonna be an important one
in many ways for this podcast
because this kind of lays out the method of what we're doing.
And we're not claiming this is all 100% perfect to correct to whatever, but it's certainly
to me anyways, does seem to represent what it is the church fathers are doing, to represent
what it is that are happening in the divine services, right?
To represent what's happening within scripture when you see people in scripture interpreting
and applying scripture, right?
And so, but far from being a kind of just
giving a sort of mechanism or technique,
because that's not what we're about.
The point of seeing the scriptures, for instance,
as an integrated whole, right, that there's not,
even though there are old covenant,
there's an old covenant and a new covenant,
that these are not disconnected from each other, right?
Like we talked about Hagel earlier,
having at least this one good thing to say
about, you know, in his case, philosoph.
not just coming out of earlier ones, but actually resting on them.
You know, you can't throw away the earlier stuff.
The same is true with Christianity, right?
You know, a lot of, for instance, a lot of people who convert to Orthodox Christianity
weirdly stop reading the Bible, you know, that they might have been reading before.
And they're like, well, I kind of got it that down. So now I want to do the fathers.
This is where it really is located.
you know, this is where the truth really really is.
But that's violating what the fathers themselves do. They're constantly going back to Scripture. They're constantly referring people to Scripture.
The Church does not treat their writings on a higher level than the Scriptures. It's clearly
the other way. The Scriptures are central. The Scriptures are always being read to us in Church services.
The Scriptures are what we're participating with ritually, over and over. That should be our whole life.
Right, and so the purpose of
of trying to understand the Scripture.
is St. John writes at the end of his gospel that we may believe and that we believe that Jesus is
the Christ and believing that it's just a being faithful, we may have life in his name. The purpose is
for our salvation. Right. And so I hope that one of the takeaways that people have is that all of this
is worth it. It's truly, truly worth it. I mean, it's one of our constant themes that this podcast
is not just about like weird crazy obscure Bible stuff or you know things dug up in the Turkish
But is it is for our salvation?
Scripture is for our salvation.
Understanding these things is for our salvation.
Can you be saved without this intellectual understanding?
Absolutely.
But if you have the capability, then you have the responsibility
to use all of your capability in the service of Christ.
And so if you have the ability to study the Scriptures
and to understand them more deeply, then that is our responsibility.
That's what we're supposed to be doing.
Right? And it's been beautiful to me to see many people become excited about reading the Bible again in the conversations that we're having.
And I think that the excitement comes, at least I hope, not just from, like I said, nerdy, weird Bible stuff, but an excitement of encountering Christ, truly encountering Christ.
And I think that to me the biggest thing to take away from this conversation this evening is...
that that encounter with Christ comes in obedience to Christ.
It comes in obedience to Christ.
This is not an esoteric experience.
This is not a scholarly experience.
It's an experience of becoming conformed to who he is.
And that this knowledge that we're discussing
is about bringing us more into that.
And I know that I find myself encouraged
by these conversations.
to head in that direction and God willing, you know, a little bit more and more I try to do that.
Father Steven?
Yeah, so sort of our whole
raison d'etre with the show is to talk about the spiritual world, right? The spiritual level
of reality that we've kind of forgotten about, you know, our modern and
those modern materialism.
And what we've been talking about tonight,
at least where it went, which hopefully now after hearing
all this about methodology, you understand that each episode
goes somewhere.
That where it went is critically important
to understanding.
Because this show isn't supposed to be about like,
Oh, there's the spiritual warfare going on out.
there and the Bible tells us about it so we can imagine it or think about it or know about it.
It's the one to know that we're involved in it, right? And of course, our leader is our Lord and
God in Saviour Jesus Christ. If you want to come to know Him better, if you want to go to where He is,
If you want to encounter him, if you want to be transformed by him, if you want to...
work with him if you want to fight alongside him, right? Then there's a place
where that's happening, right? There's a place where that's happening. And it's
not a limited or restricted place. It's potentially every place, every space,
every moment of your life. That includes the liturgical services of the
church that are sort of the center and the nexus of it. That's sort of like the
base camp. Right? And we can...
certainly encounter Christ within the services of the church,
through the scriptures as they're read in the church,
through the scriptures as they're read in our home.
But we also encounter Christ, perhaps most powerfully
and most transformatively as we were saying there
at the end, in action.
We've been doing the liturgy of St. Basil the Great
here in Great Lent.
So we, as a priest, I read all the long prayers.
And my choir usually...
finishes early, so people get to hear some of those long prayers. Well, I finished them.
But one of the many things that at various points has struck me in those long prayers,
is that describes God as the help of the helpless, the hope of the hopeless, the physician
of the sick, right? And this isn't just a hypothetical. This isn't stuff God is willing to do if
we ask or ways of praising him.
This is what...
God is actually doing.
If you want to know where Christ is right now,
he is with the people who are sick, the people who are alienated
and suffering, the people who are alone
and who are lonely, the people who are hopeless,
the people who are helpless.
That's where he is.
That's what the Scriptures tell us over and over again.
And we can go to those people and we can find him there.
We can encounter him there.
We can work with him.
there to help those who are helpless, to give hope to those who are hopeless, to help heal
and bring comfort to the sick and the suffering.
When we do that, we not only encounter Christ, but we encounter Christ in a way that changes
and transforms us.
Not where we learn some things intellectually, when we become smarter, we're better able
to win arguments on the Internet.
We can teach other people.
transformed in a way that makes us whole.
What's broken in us that gives us hope for the hopelessness that each of us has that gives us help for the helplessness that each of us has
Because comfort in the suffering that every one of us faces
And so the study of the scriptures always has to be directed out
That's to be directed out in this application
right? It has to be directed out to the world because
Christ is in the business of saving the world. That's what he's about. That's what he's doing.
Any other pursuit, whether it's an intellectual pursuit, scholarly pursuit, any other vain pursuit,
right, is not what he's about. And so that's not where we're going to find him.
So, if anything in this show is interested to you, if you think any of it is true,
That's half a spiritual world, spiritual warfare, any of it.
that, then we have a very easy way to join the fight because the people who need you, the people
who Christ loves and is caring for are all around you every day. We just have to be willing
to actually do it, to actually participate, to actually help, and to actually love them also.
Well, that is our show for tonight. Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
If you can't get through to us.
live, we would still love to hear from you. You can email us at Lordofspiritsatainstfaith.com,
you can message us at our Facebook page, or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com
slash Lordofspirits. I do listen to all the speak types. Yeah. Join us for our live broadcast on
the second and fourth Thursday of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. And if you are on Facebook,
you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most
most importantly share the
show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally be sure to go to www.hinksandface.com, stroke support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasts are stay on the air and Bobby gets those lawyers guns and money.
Thank you. Good night and may God bless you and I hope you have a blessed holy week and
a bright and beautiful POSCO.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain.
to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.